<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The English monsieur a comical novel : wherein his travells, amours, and other passages of his life no less strange than delightful, are faithfully set down by an impartial hand : in four parts.</title>
            <author>Howard, James, fl. 1672-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 93 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44634</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2981_VARIANT</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31537</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12083737</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12083737</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53678</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44634)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53678)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1012:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The English monsieur a comical novel : wherein his travells, amours, and other passages of his life no less strange than delightful, are faithfully set down by an impartial hand : in four parts.</title>
                  <author>Howard, James, fl. 1672-1674.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 166 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Cademan ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Howard by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: contains only the first part.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English fiction --  Early modern, 1500-1700.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53678:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53678:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Engliſh Monſieur A COMICAL NOVEL. WHEREIN His Travells, Amours, and other Paſſages of his life, no leſs ſtrange than delightful, are faithfully ſet down, by an Impartial hand. In Four Parts.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Si mea Landas</l>
               <l>Omnia, ſtultitiam; ſi nihil Invidiam.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Cademan</hi> at the Popes head in the New-<hi>Exchange</hi> in the <hi>Strand</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:53678:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53678:2"/>
            <head>To my Honored Friend <hi>E. H.</hi> Eſq;</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN an age, when books had better be burnt for Hereticks, than pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to appear with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the dull formality of an Epiſtle; ſuch a notable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect would preſent them in as rediculous a <hi>Querpo,</hi> as a Courtier without the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of his Sword, though to both equally uſeleſs; therefore, leaſt I ſhould be taxed with too much ignor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb facs="tcp:53678:3"/> or preſumption, to you who are our petty Heroes particular friend, and the depoſitary of his greateſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets. To you, who have been an eye witneſs of ſome of the moſt remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able inconveniences that his natural curioſity, reſtleſs diſpoſition, Amours, Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and fiery nature have plung'd him in: finally to you, that by conſequence can beſt diſcerne what fruits are of his own growth, from what he may have borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from his neighbours Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards, I dedicate theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſheets. I am ſenſible
<pb facs="tcp:53678:3"/> that now I ſhould proceed to the ſetting forth of your praiſes, and humbly ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate for your generous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, but really I am ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle accuſtom'd to the flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtile of a Dedication, that I know not what more to ſay, therefore would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take the opportunity to end with the general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of, Sir, your moſt humble ſervant, <hi>B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then, what would the Bookſeller ſay? who yet does expect ſo much ſcribbling as muſt fill up ſome empty pages of the laſt ſheet? why Faith to
<pb facs="tcp:53678:4"/> pleaſe all parties (if it be poſſible) <hi>I</hi> will make bold to lay you aſide, and ſpeak a word or two to the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reader, and that I hope will do the jobb.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, <hi>I</hi> will let him know, that he will find here ſuch varieties of humours, as, I hope, will pleaſe him, provided he adds not a number amongſt the peripatetick Cinicks. To ſuch I muſt confeſs theſe things would prove eyeſores, at leaſt if not a <hi>Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Magnatum,</hi> but to the Gay, Ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, and witty ſort this may be uſeful while
<pb facs="tcp:53678:4"/> they leave the knoty points of the more moroſe part of learning to be cleav'd in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with the Beetles of the ſowr Philoſophers under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            <p>In the firſt part you will meet with ſuch accidents as wild young Travellers are apt to fall into, and if you pleaſe, you may make good uſe of them; In the ſecond you will be diverted with the extravagant conceits of a <hi>Roſycrucians</hi> chymereal Philoſophy, and ſublime learning in the obſtruce Sciences. In the third your imagination will be tickled
<pb facs="tcp:53678:5"/> (eſpecially if ever you have put your noſe in a chymical Author) with ſome quaint expoſitions of the moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult points, on all things ſuch as the envious malice or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited ignorance of ſome Writers have left to poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, wrapp'd up in thoſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious riddles, that moſt wonderfully do puzle this age, and will fit the next for New <hi>Bedlame.</hi> But <hi>I</hi> adviſe you not to pin your Faith on all I ſay, for it may not in every point prove to be Madam truth in its <hi>puris naturalibus.</hi> And why you ſhould expect to find more
<pb facs="tcp:53678:5"/> reality in a Romantick ſtory then in the Alchymiſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly grave Vollumes, <hi>I</hi> know not, except, <hi>Ridendo dicere verum,</hi> come in your mind, and delude you into the fooles Paradice. Well take your chance friend, while I inform you, that in the fourth part you will meet with the fruits and reſults of raſh youth, when once it makes its own ſword a Law, and every indifferent object the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of his affections.</p>
            <p>Now Curteous Reader, but that I think you wiſer than my ſelf, I would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe
<pb facs="tcp:53678:6"/> you to follow what is good in the whole, (If you can find any) and ſo to take warning by others harms, as to go to bed in a whole skin, and the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſing to the tune of ſome new Ballad.</p>
            <q>Felix quem faciunt, aliena pericula cautum.</q>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:53678:6"/>
            <head>Playes Sold by <hi>William Cademan</hi> at the Popes head in the New <hi>Exchange.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>RIvals a Comedy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cataline.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Iſland Princeſs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Flora's</hi> Vagaries.</item>
               <item>Town Shifts.</item>
               <item>Citizen turned Gentleman.</item>
               <item>Morning Rambles.</item>
               <item>Fatal jealouſie.</item>
               <item>Macbeth.</item>
               <item>all writ by <hi>Elkana Settle</hi> Gent.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cambyſes.</hi> 
                     </item>
                     <item>Empreſs of <hi>Morocco.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Mariamne.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Notes on <hi>Morocco.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Conqueſt of <hi>Chyna.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ibrahim.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Paſtor Fido.</item>
                     <item>Love and Revenge.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Careleſs Lovers.</item>
               <item>Engliſh Princeſs.</item>
               <item>Reformation.</item>
               <item>Spaniſh Rogue.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Marcellia.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Mall.</item>
               <item>Rehearſal.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:53678:7"/>
               <item>Mock Tempeſt.</item>
               <item>Dumb Lady.</item>
               <item>Gentleman Dancing Maſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Alcibiades.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dutch Lovers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pyſa</hi>'s Conſpiracy.</item>
               <item>Seige of <hi>Nemphis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Rivall Kings.</item>
               <item>Conſtant Nymph.</item>
               <item>Wrangling Lovers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tom Eſſence.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>French Conjurer.</item>
               <item>Wits led by the Noſe.</item>
               <item>Counterfeit Bridegroome.</item>
               <item>Tunbridge Wells.</item>
               <item>Man of New-market.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Northempton</hi> in her flames.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53678:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE English Monſieur <hi>A Comical Novel.</hi> The Firſt Part.</head>
            <p>IN the Chief City of <hi>England</hi> there dwelt a married Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who, though they had nor ſuch Fortune as to raiſe them to the firſt Rank. They enjoy'd a ſufficient Eſtate to maintain themſelves in a handſome mediocrity above the Vulgar.</p>
            <p>One only Child had been the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of their twenty years Love, on whom they had beſtowed an Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion rather beyond their Rank then ſutable to it. <hi>Noble</hi> was his Name,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53678:8"/> he had not attained to his Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth year, when his Parents were forced to part with their onely Joy, and all their hopes, by ſending him beyond Sea, thereby to reclaim and wean him from ſome company very unfitting his Age and condition, with whom he had unhappily acquainted himſelf, but all other means having been endeavour'd in vain, there was none left but that, which had ſo well ſucceeded to the Father, when about his Sons years, that they hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the ſame good ſucceſs towards the Son.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Noble</hi> was of an indifferent ſize, ſmall timber'd not very ſtrong, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently quick, active, of ſanguine fair complexion, and of a Reſtleſs diſpoſition; he had an inclination to travel, and being of a quick appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, and agreeable converſation, it rendred him acceptable to all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of either Sex, eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Female, his natural con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution inclining him to <hi>Venus</hi> her worſhip, to the neglect of <hi>Bacchus</hi> his ſervice.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:53678:8"/>
            <p>He had gone through the Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Latine Tongue, attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a perfection in the French, and received ſome inſtructions from Eminent Maſters in Muſick, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicks, Drawing, Fencing and ſuch like gentile Exerciſes, when he forced his Parents to this Reſolution, ſo contrary to their deſigns, and ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to his own Genius.</p>
            <p>Our young Traveller, was fitted with all things neceſſary for his Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and an aſſurance of a Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent yearly allowance, ſo long as they ſhould hear of his civil Converſation, and the following of his exerciſes: The day of his departure, Letters of Recommendations were given him to divers perſons of Note and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute in <hi>Paris,</hi> with a Bill of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change for a ſupply of monies, to ſet him in the French mode ſo ſoon as arrived. The tender Mother's tear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, with her private Golden bleſſing ended the Adieus. The next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, very early, up gets our Stripling, and directs his courſe towards <hi>Dover,</hi> where he met with a favourable paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53678:9"/> to <hi>Calis,</hi> there having joyn'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the company of the Stage Coach (though on a ſtout Gelding) they ſet forward for <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt day of their journey the Coach found it very difficult to paſs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a certain ſmall brook, which was overflown by a ſudden fall of Rain, which made the Company reſolve to take up in ſome place on this ſide <hi>Paris,</hi> rather than hazard the paſſage. They therefore deſired our young Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant to ride before to a certain Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, which they pointed at, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeak a good Supper for the whole Company. <hi>Le Noble</hi> glad of any op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to oblige his fellow Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, gives no Anſwer, but flacking the Reins of his Bridle, made with a good ſpeed towards the place, lights at an Inn, where having taken care of his Beaſt, he beſpeaks a handſome Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for ſeven or eight perſons, which would aſſuredly be there within an hour at ſurtheſt. In an inſtant mine Hoſt gives out the Orders unto all the Officers under him, and they Execute them with dilligence eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53678:9"/> one according to his Station.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Noble,</hi> mean time having eſpy'd a young Maid, who was preparing of Candlos to light this new come Gueſt to his Chamber, and perceiving that ſhe had a certain Ayr and Meen, which was more pleaſing than in ſuch ordinary perſons is commonly found, began a diſcourſe, whereby to try, whether her Wit was anſwerable to her pritty outſide. He had but juſt found out by her quick, yet modeſt reparties, that ſhe was ſomething more than a Inn-Keepers Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid, when ſhe was call'd to her bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, which broke off the diſcourſe, but it had been ſoon renewed again by our young Traveller, who would have found out ſome opportunity to have accoſted her again, had not two Mendicant Friers diverted him from it by demanding his Charity, in a pritty kind of obliging Dialect: He having formerly heard that ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are very pleaſing and agrocable Company, did deſign to divert him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with theſe two good Brothers till Supper time; and leave his other
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53678:10"/> Game till after Supper; with that he falls in diſcourſe with them, and deſires their Company till Supper time, that then they ſhould not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have their ſhare of it, but carry the reſidue along with them. For, good Reader, you are to know, that thoſe kind of Mendicants never car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry money about them, it being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Rules of their Order to ask for, or receive any. The good Friers accepted <hi>Le Nobles</hi> kind offer, and after a Glaſs or two of Wine, began to be in their uſual witty and modeſt Mirth; and then came out a multitude of very pleaſant Stories: of which thoſe perſons are alwaies as well provided, as are our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Fidlers with Songs, ſutable to all humours and Companies, though ever accompanied with more modeſty. This made the time paſs merrily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and the Coach not ſeem ſo long in coming, though it had paſs'd it's hour. While they were all on their jokes, in comes mine Hoſt fuming and puffing, ſwearing by all the fiery Gods, that the meat was almoſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53678:10"/> ſpoil'd, and yet no News of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, while the Hoſt was thus venting that heat, which he had contracted at the fire, in comes a Meſſenger, with notice, that the Coach, having found out a by way was gone directly to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris;</hi> theſe news one would think, ſhould have ſtruck our Traveller in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a conſternation, but nothing leſs appear'd in his looks; on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, having bid the Hoſt to ſerve up Supper, he told the Friers that he was glad to have met with their good Company, which with that of his Hoſt, would be ſufficient to divert him from Reflecting on this croſs ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, which concern'd him no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than the not meeting with ſome friends, that would expect him that night at <hi>Paris.</hi> But it matters not, continued he, I ſhall be there early in the morning, mean time Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the ſatisfaction I receive by your good Company, makes a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient return for my ſtay here this night; this Complement ended, while the good Friers were making ſome excuſes, up come the fore-runners of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53678:11"/> the Feaſt, and according to the French dilligence, in a moment the Cloth was laid, the Diſhes placed in order, the Wine ſet in Tubs of water to Cool, the Glaſſes waſh'd, and in a word all in a decent readineſs, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wanting to begin the onſet, but the word of Command, which is uſually expreſs'd by a Benedicite. The Company had not been long ſet but news was brought up to the Hoſt, that the Curate was below that would ſpeak with him, at which the Hoſt ſaid, Sirs, this Curate of our Pariſh here, is the beſt Company of the World, he is for all humours and conſtitutions, will you be merry, no man hath better Stories, will you be ſerious, he is a Saint, would you play, he knows all Games and tricks, would you drink, that is his Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. In ſhort, Sir, he is for what any Company pleaſes, and I aſſure you, you will receive a ſingular ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in his Company if you p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſe to admit him into yours. <hi>Le Noble</hi> needed no further inducement, he quickly gave order that he ſhould be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53678:11"/> brought up: the Curate was no ſooner enter'd the Chamber, but he ſets himſelf down, and having ſaid, Gentlemen, you may think ſtrange at my abrupt intruſion into your Company, without the leaſt Complement, but you muſt know, that beſides my natural anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy towards them, I find, that in the poſture you all are, I ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice my ſelf very much in delaying to carry on the work of the day, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally it being ſo near a concluſion, with that he fell on, every fift or ſixt bit cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for Wine, which he would take moſt diſdainfully from the Waiter, if no brimmer, and ſpoke not a word more till the Cloath was taken away. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Supper, the two good Friers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated divers pritty pleaſant Stories and all freely took their Cups. After Supper the Curate did highly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence his long ſilence, there was no talk but for him, which he made up ſo pleaſantly with Songs and Ralle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that no time could be more pleaſingly ſpent. Amongſt the reſt of his Stories, I ſhall give you here an account of his laſt, which he Uſher'd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53678:12"/> in with this preamble to the two good Friers (who were then filling their Bugdets with the reſidue of the Meat according to <hi>Le Noble</hi>'s order.) Brothers, ſaid he, I ſee you are now providing for your March, and I think it is high time, leaſt you find the Gates of your Covent ſhut againſt you, and ſo be obliged, not much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your wills, to take up your nights Lodgings at ſome good neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring houſe, to the good mans di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance, though peradventure with the good liking of the Wife, her Daughter, Maid, or all three, rather than diſoblige any of them. But before you go, pray give me leave to relate what a pritty kind of Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, one of your Order required from a pritty young, but very ſilly woman. I muſt confeſs, (anſwer'd one of the good Friers) that we were wondring that you had ſpared us ſo long, contrary to your uſual Cuſtome, but do your worſt, we will give you a <hi>Rowland</hi> for your <hi>Oliver,</hi> and begin when you pleaſe. At theſe Menaces, have at you ſaid the Curate, and thus he began his Story.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:53678:12"/>
               <head>The Curate<hi>'s</hi> Tale.</head>
               <p>A Certain Good man, who had lately married a young Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, againſt a good time was telling his Wife, that he deſign'd to go to Confeſſion, and that he would have her to do the like, ſhe excus'd her ſelf by informing her Husband, that ſhe having never yet been at Confeſſion, did not know the manner of it, nor knew ſhe to whom ſhe ſhould addreſs her ſelf, ſweetheart, ſaid the good man to his Wife, in the Monaſtery of the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melites,</hi> there is a certain Religious man of my acquaintance, to whom I will recommend you, for my ſake he will inſtruct you, and will ſhrive you very well, ſo giving his Wife the name of the Frier, he ſends her to the Covent. The good woman got thither inquires after the Frier, and ſhe is ordered to wait for him in the Church; not long after comes unto her the party, who inquires what ſhe deſired; to which with a Curteſie, ſhe made An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that her Husband, ſuch a one
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53678:13"/> had ſent her to him to confeſſion, knowing that he was a godly man, and ſhe young and unexperienc'd in ſuch matters. At this the Frier pricks up his ears, and within his heart thanks his good fate, for preſenting him with ſo good a Fortune, with that he takes her to an obſcure place of the Church, where he us'd to confeſs others, and there, he holding her by the hand, began his Interrogations, and through his diligent Care and good Inſtructions, he made the Innocent Creature anſwer very directly unto all his queſtions. The Frier by this time having found by the ſillineſs of her own Anſwers, that ſhe was much Fairer than Wife, he reſolv'd to bear up cloſe to her, continuing his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in this manner. My dear Child, hitherto you have anſwer'd very punctually to all my queſtions, and accordingly I ſhall abſolve you, but there is yet remaining one thing in which you muſt be very juſt, or you will commit a very great Sacriledge. Therefore be ſure to give me a very exact account of what I am going to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53678:13"/> ask of you. The poor ſilly Creature having made anſwer with a yea, Sir, and a ſhort Curteſie, he drawing her ſtill more in the dark, ſo that they could be perceived! It is my kindneſs to you, ſaid he, which makes me lead you ſo in the dark, that you may with more freedom anſwer to what I ſhall ask you, and with that holding her by the hand with one hand, and under the Chin with the other, dear Child, continued he, how often has your Husband lain with you? Be ſure you Anſwer me juſtly, and hid nothing from me? At thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſilly young thing, anſwer'd with a great ſigh, truly ſo often with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſs of the half year they had been married, that it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for her to know the number. At this Anſwer, the Frier ſeeming much ſurpriz'd, how ſaid he, not know the number, how can the Church have the Tithe then? And how can you hope for an abſolution ſo long as you withold the Church of its rights; I am very ſorry, continued he, that you are in ſo dangerous a condition, and for the Love I bear you, and by reaſon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53678:14"/> of your want of knowledge in ſuch matters, I would gladly find out ſome way to redreſs this great error, thus went the Frier on ſtill aggravating each Circumſtance, which ſo affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the poor ſilly woman, that ſhe fell trembling upon her knees at the Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers feet, and all in Tears and Sobs earneſtly begg'd, that he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive ſome way to abſolve her from this ſo hainous a ſin, ſeeing that ſhe had committed it out of meer ignorance, and that her Husband was very much to blame, that he had not given her timely notice of it; and humbly intreated him to take the Tithes himſelf, as much as he thought fit, and rather more than leſs, that ſhe might be abſolutely freed and abſolved from that grievous ſin. The good Frier did what he could to appeaſe her, and having ſetled her mind a little by his comfortable ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, he told her, that for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, he would be contented with ſome ſmall part of the Tithes, but that he would take a longer time to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute what was due in all, for as he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53678:14"/> would not have the Church to loſe any advantage, neither would he for the World wrong her good Husband of the worth of a pin, with that he takes her by the Arm and conveys her by a ſecret paſſage into his Chamber, where he took what part of the Tithe he pleas'd, which having done and kiſſing the young Woman, go, my Child, ſaid he, and be chearful, I ſhall come ſometimes at your houſe, to take the reſt of the Tithes, but one thing more I muſt inform you of before you go, know that is a mortal ſin for any one to reveal any the leaſt part of Confeſſion, therefore you muſt be ſure not to declare, by any means ſoever, either to your Husband or any body eſle, what has paſs'd between you and me, for if you do, you will be damn'd for ever without redemption. To which the Penitent woman having anſwer'd, that ſhe would be ſure to keep ſilence, and deſiring him once more to take a larger quantity of the remaining Tithes, leaſt any evil ſhould happen to her or her Husband, by detaining them any longer, he to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53678:15"/> gratifie her, and put her out of all fears, did make a further deduction of the arrears, and ſo diſmiſs'd her the ſame way ſhe had come in, with his bleſſing, ſending her home to the good man her Husband, with an aſſurance that he would come to her houſe and take the reſt of the Tithes, when ever ſhe would give him notice of her Husbands abſence. The Curate had proceeded ſo far, when one of the Friers with a great deal of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiency did thus Interrupt his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
               <p>I have had much patience to hear you ſpeak all this while, though all that you have ſaid is very true, and that the Story goes on a great way further, but that which makes me thus impatient at preſent is, that you ſhould have the confidence to put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any religious Order, that of which you your ſelf are guilty, you being the very perſon that did this hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid act, for which you were deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly puniſhed by the Husband and afterwards turn'd out of that Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, which you had then in a Church
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53678:15"/> in the City of <hi>Lyons,</hi> where this fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Sacriledge of yours was commited, I happened at that time to be there, and I remember you very well: How you came to be entertain'd Vicar in this place, I wonder at, but I aſſure you, that I will make a ſtrict inquiry after it, and have you puniſhed as you deſerve, being ſo great a ſcandal to the whole Church.</p>
               <p>The good Frier would have gone on, and perhaps his Zeal to Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and his abomination of ſuch Crimes would have occaſion'd a Learned de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation againſt ſuch Sacrilegious perſons, but that the Hoſt willing to befriend the Curate (who was one of his conſtant gueſs) interrupted the good Frier, deſiring him to forbear at preſent any further diſcourſe on that ſubject.</p>
               <p>The Curate at this was not mute, but in a Chaffing manner told the Company, that he would maintain all that he had ſaid was of a <hi>Carmelite</hi> Frier, that he knew him very well, that he would immediately go fetch ſome Writings in which they all ſhould
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53678:16"/> ſee the Name and Sirname of the perſons concerned, and where and at what time this was done; ſo in a great fury he went down Stairs. Mean time, the good Frier having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated <hi>Le Noble</hi> to give him but one quarter of an hours attention, that he might juſtifie his Order, and ſet the ſaddle on the right Horſe, he thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd the Story.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The continuance of the Curates Story.</head>
               <p>YOu have already heard the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Villanies of this wicked Curate from his own mouth, though he would gladly lay it upon ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the crime appearing ſo hainous to himſelf; that he is aſhamed to own it, I will begin where he left off, and that he is that very perſon, I ſhall prove to morrow by undeniable evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences.</p>
               <p>This abominable man, being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient to purſue what he had ſo wickedly began, ſtaid not long till he went to viſit this abuſed young Woman, and his viſits grew ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53678:16"/> that at laſt, the good Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band having ſome kind of ſuſpition of the buſineſs, did one day wait for this beaſtly man, and ſoon did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap him ploughing with his Heifer. The Prieſt (for ſo he was then) finding himſelf diſcovered withdrew to his home as ſuddenly and ſecretly as he could poſſible. And the poor abuſed Husband having found by the Silly Anſwers, which his ſimple In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Wife made to his queſtions about the buſineſs, that ſhe had been, through her great ſimplicity, moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominably abuſed by this wicked fellows ſubtle and devilliſh practices; he was not angry with her, but having inſtructed and admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her, he left her very ſorrowful and penſive, and immediately went to complain to the Biſhop, of the abuſe done unto him in the perſon of his Wife. The Biſhop, with much pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence heard out the poor man's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, and ſeeming very angry, gave order that the Prieſt ſhould immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately be ſent for, which was accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly done, ſo ſoon as he was in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53678:17"/> the Biſhops preſence; he asked him in a very angry and furious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, what tempted him to do ſo wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a thing, and after many threats and chidings, not giving him once leave to anſwer, he told him, that he would ſeverely puniſh him for it, after theſe and many more big ſpeeches having firſt diſmiſs'd all that were in the Room, but the Plantiff and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent, he ſtrictly did forbid him ever for any more ſeting his foot into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd man's houſe, nor ever to dare to ſpeak to his Wife, or ſo much as look upon her, and for a further puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he charg'd him upon pain of Excommunication, not to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any Church during three whole dayes, and ſo diſmiſs'd them both. The Prieſt went home much diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented that he ſhould no longer have ſo eaſie an acceſs, as he had formerly to the good man's Wife, but what troubled him worſt of all was the fears, that the Husband had diſabus'd his poor innocent Wife, and better inform'd her for the future, ſo that he ſhould be put to new practices,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53678:17"/> before he could reclaim her again. As concerning his excluſion from Church, it fitted ſo well his humour and inclinations, that he was the better pleas'd with it, becauſe it gave him more leaſure to retire and contrive new ways to once more Inſnare that poor innocent ſoul.</p>
               <p>The Husband on the other hand being not at all contented, with ſuch a ſort of ſatisfaction as he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the Biſhop, reſolves to make his complaint to the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the City, with that he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately goes to his appartment, and acquaints him with the whole Story, and moſt earneſtly begg'd upon his knees, that he would do him ſuch Juſtice, as were ſuitable to the offence he had received, ſince that he could not have it from the Biſhop, who of Right was to have done it. The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, who was a perſon of as great irregrity and goodneſs, as he was punctual and ſevere in his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, told the poor fellow, that it was out of his power to do him Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; but continued he, yet I would
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53678:18"/> not have ſuch notorious villanies paſs unpuniſhed, therefore honeſt friend ſince thou canſt not get any other redreſs from the Biſhop then what thou haſt mention'd unto me, which is ſo inſignificant, and I knowing by very good informations, that both the Biſhop and Prieſt are perſons of lewd Lives and Converſation, I do adviſe thee that the next time thou find'ſt the Prieſt to attempt any thing upon thy Wife, thou gets ſome friends to aſſiſt thee, and having in trap'd him, Gudgle him to ſome purpoſe, but take care of killing him, or breaking any of his Limbs, and when thou haſt done come to me, and declare before thoſe perſons, that I ſhall have there on purpoſe, the whole buſineſs both of the wrong done thee, the Biſhops ſentence againſt the offender, and thy reven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> upon him, and let me alone with the reſt, I ſhall take care that no hurt ſhall come to thee thereby. The good man, having thank'd the Governour, goes his way home again with a firm reſolution to have his full Revenge, and to that purpoſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53678:18"/> watches the Prieſt narrowly, and admoniſhes his Wife to do the like, which ſhe gladly undertook, being highly incenſed againſt him, now that her Husband had undeceived her. They both were not long before they had an opportunity preſented them, for the Laſcivous Prieſt think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the time long till he were at his beaſtly Embraces again, though the three dayes Pennance were not yet fully expired, writ a paſſionate kind Letter to the young Woman, and had it privately convey'd to her by an Old woman, that us'd to be employ'd by him in ſuch Embaſſies, who found an opportunity to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it privately into the young Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans hands, who going into ſome other place, as if to Read it in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, ſhe gave it to her Husband, who having opened it found writ in it as follows.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:53678:19"/>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>My dear Child,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> Make no queſtion, but tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> thy Husband through an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of Jealouſie, and contempt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Holy Church, has put ſtrang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> things into thy head, as if wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> we have done together were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Juſt and Lawful, not conſiderin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> that whatſoever is done with right intention, (though it migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſeem ſomewhat unuſual, and appe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> not very well unto Vulgar Eyes could have a ſiniſter end, No <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> dear Child, we cannot Err what ever we do, ſo long as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> direct our intentions aright, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> can they be better deſigned th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> when we aim at nothing but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> good benefit and honour of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Church, in paying and receivi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> its dues? I long to inform th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> throughly in this point which
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53678:19"/> cannot do by writing; therefore let me deſire thee, for thy own ſouls ſake, to defer no longer the payment of the reſidue of thoſe Tithes, which thy wicked Husband would defraud the Church of, give me notice then as ſoon as may; be of an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to come to thee, and then I ſhall fully inform thee of the Juſtice of the matter in hand, ſo that thou ſhalt he wholly convinced of the neceſſity of continuing our private meetings.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Letter being read, the Husband, after a little pauſe, bid his Wife tell the Meſſenger that had brought it, that the Prieſt ſhould not fail to come to her in the Orchard at midnight, where ſhe long'd to ſee him and do juſtice to the Church, that ſhe would leave the back door open, and that there they might be very ſecure from her Husbands Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, with this Anſwer away goes the Meſſenger back, who made the Prieſt overjoy'd with this moſt favourable Anſwer, applauding his own wit and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53678:20"/> ſubtlety, and longed moſt impatient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the happy hour. In the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the Husband gets in readineſs two of his neighbours with luſty Cudgels to entertain the Gallant with all, according to his deſerts, at the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed place.</p>
               <p>The hour came: into the Orchard came the Prieſt likewiſe; where in liew of the good woman's kind re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, he met with one ſomewhat more crabbed at the hands of the Hushand and his aſſiſtants. In ſhort, they all three did ſo well handle their weapons, that in a ſhort time they left the poor Lover not able to ſtir a Limb, which invited them to be ſo civil as to carry him between them at a little diſtance from the Orchard, where near a high way they left him.</p>
               <p>In the morning, when people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſtir abroad, the half dead ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was found in this condition by ſome going that way, preſently it was reported to the Biſhop, and the noiſe of it ſpread all over the City. The Prieſt is taken up, laid on a Hearſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> covered, and in great ſolemnity, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53678:20"/> demonſtration of ſorrow carried about all the quarters of the City, with a proceſſion of Prieſts following after, and the hard uſage of him told to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that inquired into the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, though not one word menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd of the cauſe thereof, all this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done by the Biſhops order; you muſt know, to ſtrike ſorrow and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſion, and that the ſevere puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which he intended to inflict up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Deliquent, ſhould be the leſs wondered at. The Governour hearing, that there was ſuch a proceſſion on foot, and not knowing the occaſion, made ſome of his Servants inquire the reaſon of it, the buſineſs being reported to him, he takes cognizance of the matter, ſends for the Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and will have a buſineſs that caus'd ſo much diſturbance in the City, to be diſcuſſed before him, and thoſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, as us'd to ſit on criminal cauſes, to aſſiſt him in a matter of ſo ſtrange a nature; the Criminal is brought before the bench, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes the fact, and withal the reaſons that did move him to do it; the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53678:21"/> come to aggravate the Crime, the Biſhop himſelf appears in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the Church, repreſents the affront done to the Clergy, and the evil conſequences of it. The Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour upon that, asks of the Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal why he had not complained to the Biſhop, if he had had any wrong done him by any of the Clergy, who doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs would have done him Juſtice, and not offer to carve to himſelf as he pleas'd out of Juſtices ſtore! To which, the poor man anſwers, that he had made his complaints to the Biſhop, but had received ſo little ſatisfaction the firſt time, and the puniſhment was ſo inſignificant to the Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, that it had not deterr'd him from committing the ſame fault over again, very ſuddenly after, ſo that he was reſolved to do himſelf Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. The Governour inquires into the manner and nature of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to know whether it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion'd to the Crime, and being Certified, that what the Malefactor had told him of the Biſhops ſentence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the Prieſt was true, he ſtood up,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53678:21"/> and pronounced this ſentence with a loud voice; For as much as the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, that ſtands at the Bar before us, has confeſſed the Crime he is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of, and that it is ſufficiently proved by the injured perſons own mouth, and the marks that remain yet upon the Body of the ill treated, which he has lately received from the ſaid perſon; I hear declare and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, that the ſaid Criminal, ſhall be ſuſpended, and is hereby ſuſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, from going into any Tavern dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing three whole dayes; and that in caſe the ſaid Delinquent does offer to ſet his foot into any Tavern, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever or whereſoever, during the ſaid time, after the giving of this ſentence, that then he ſhall be proceeded againſt, as ſhall be judged fit.</p>
               <p>This Ironical, but juſt ſentence; having produc'd much joy on the one ſide, and more ſpight and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the other. The Biſhop in the name of the Clergy, ſtood up, and ſaid, that he would appeal of this affront done to the Church in his Perſon, to a Supreme Power, ſo
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53678:22"/> went his way, with the reſt of the Crew.</p>
               <p>He was after that as good as his word, and the Governour, (who did ſtick cloſe to him and the Delinquent Prieſt) having exhibited thoſe evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, which he had gathered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them both, and the witneſſes being heard, the Biſhop was quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laid aſide, and the Prieſt degraded and turn'd out of his Benefice, all as privately as might be, that the leſs ſcandal ſhould ariſe to the Church, by the wicked actions of ſuch dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous men. Now, Sir, I have made an end of my Relation, which I will avouch to be true to a tittle.</p>
               <p>At this <hi>Le Noble</hi> riſing and return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thanks to the two good Friers, for their good company and agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble converſation, he aſſured them, that he did believe all that the Frier had ſaid, was very true, and that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as further convinced thereof, by the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates abſence, whoſe guilty Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence would not let him return. With that the Friers taking leave with many thanks, went their ways,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53678:22"/> and <hi>Le Noble</hi> gets into his bed Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, where having call'd for the Hoſt in order to pay the reckoning, that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> might be the ſooner gone in the morning. The houſe, diſcharged, he goes to make faſt his door, but find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neither Look nor Bolt to it, he did make a barricado againſt it, of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat he could find in his Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; and then he flings himſelf upon the bed in his Gloaths, with his Piſtols, and his Sword by him, having left the Candle burning in the Chimney.</p>
               <p>Some hours after, our Traveller being in a profound ſleep, he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened out of it with the great noiſe, that thoſe things which he had ſet againſt the Door, upon the Table made in falling, he throws himſelf off of the Bed, betwixt aſleep and awake, full of fears, and in ſo doing makes one of his Piſtols fall on the ground behind him, which went off and preſently he heard ſome body cry out murther, the fright which he was in before being ſo great, he preſently fancied that the Piſtol had been ſhot at him, this ſtruck him
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53678:23"/> into ſuch a terrour, that he fancied a thouſand perſons were at hand, with Swords and Piſtols to murther him, which made him ſtand ſtock ſtill, not daring almoſt to breath, much leſs to ſpeak.</p>
               <p>After ſome time, finding that all was quiet his door ſhut and no body near him, he began to move and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to cry out, <hi>Qui va la,</hi> hearing no body anſwer him, he ſteps to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the door, and makes up his Barricado again, then retiring towards the Bed ſees a ſolded Paper lye at his feet, he takes it up and finds this writ in it.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>SIr, there is a deſign in this houſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your Life, go not in Bed but ſtand upon your guard all night, and keep your door well ſhut. But I will break their meaſures or loſe my Life, ſo long at <hi>Suſetta</hi> is your Champion you need not fear.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>Le Noble,</hi> ſoon perceiv'd that it came from the Maid, he had been fooling with the Evening before, but
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53678:23"/> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd very much at the ſtile and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, much better than might be expected from a common Servant, which made him think that ſhe was ſomething more, then what ſhe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd to be, this brought into his mind, that during his Jeſting with her, he had found her full of quick repartees, a good diſcourſe, an obliging modeſt way, and quite of another ayr, than that of an Inn-keepers maid. This began to work upon his fancy wonderfully, and repreſenting to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf her pritty ſhape, her black eyes and hairs, and her excellent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion; if it did not produce Love in his heart, yet it created a great eſteem for her in his mind, which was very apt to take fire, he ſpent the reſt of the night, in muſing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on this Theam, ſo ſoon as break of day appear'd, he heard <hi>Suſetta</hi> making towards his Chamber door, ſinging this Song.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>The Enemies gone, the Coaſt is clear.</l>
                  <l>'Tis time for <hi>Damon</hi> to appear.</l>
               </q>
               <p>This delivered with a good voice, ſhe knocks at the door, <hi>Le Noble</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53678:24"/> who it was by her voice, preſently opens to her, who then appearing to him a thouſand times prittier, in that negligent morning dreſs ſhe was in, that made an end of his liberty; his ſtanding mute, gaping upon her, gave her time to ſpeak thus, Good morrow to you, Sir, I fear you have not had much reſt this night, but it is well you are come off at ſo cheap a rate, I hope, you will pardon the boldneſs that I take, to intrude thus in your Chamber this morning, when you know it is in orders to your further ſafety, I perceive that you have read that note, which I convey'd into your Chamber laſt night under the door, when you were faſt? And making as if ſhe would take it out of <hi>Le Noble</hi>'s hands; pray, Sir, continued ſhe, tare that pitiful Seribling: pitiful Scrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, reply'd, <hi>Le Noble.</hi> it is a jewel, and for the pritty Scriblers ſake I'le wear it here, with that he puts it into his boſome. Oh fie, Sir, ſaid ſhe then, do not defile your skin, with the touch of what a dirty Chamber maid has handled: That has made
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53678:24"/> it the more bright, reply'd, <hi>Le Noble,</hi> and that high eſteem I have for it, proceeds from the luſter, that that pritty Chamber-maid, as you call her, has communicated to it, by the ſweet influence of her hand. Nay, Sir, if you begin to Complement, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd <hi>Suſetta,</hi> I muſt leave you, for beſides that I know they muſt be all ſlatteries; which you ſpeak of me, ſuch poor Creatures as we are, know not how to anſwer them, therefore let me intreat you, Sir, to forbear, and give me leave to inform you of the occaſion of my coming to you ſo early, with that <hi>Le Noble</hi> taking her by the hand and leading her to the bed ſide, where with much ado he oblig'd her to ſie down by him, he told her, that he was very much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to her, for her care of his ſate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and deſtred her to relate him how ſhe came by that knowledge: Sir, ſaid ſhe, not long after you had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired into your Chamber, I going to the place where I lie, perceiv'd a light through a Chink which was in a back room below ſtairs; where ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53678:25"/> rarely any perſon enters. I think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that every body was gone to Bed, it made me the more curious to know on what occaſion it was there, I came as near as I could to that place through which I had ſeen the light, and there I ſpy'd my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and the Curate that was with you the laſt night; this ſtill increas'd my curioſity, which made me lend an ear to their diſcourſe, I could hear the Curate ſay, it is not that which troubles me, Damn the Frier? That which I fear, is to be arreſted to morrow morning, and to have a Child la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to my charge, thoſe are the cauſes of my troubles, which how to remove, I know not, but by removing my ſelf. But how is that to be done, reply'd my Maſter: I have a way ſaid the Curate, if you would but aſſiſt in it: To tell you the truth, reply'd my Maſter, I am in a worſe condition then you are, and therefore let us lay our heads to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and aſſiſt one another as well as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can, for I have not above a day, or two's time to look about me,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53678:25"/> the worſt on't is, that I have no horſe, I ſhould not want money long, if I had a good one: is there not a good one in the ſtable, ſaid the Curate? It is but ridding your ſelf of his Maſter, and the beaſt is your own, for any part I'le make uſe of the beſt of thoſe two Jades, that are in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Stable, and take my fortune with you, at whatſoe're you pleaſe: you propoſe what is not amiſs, reply'd my Maſter, but the way to do it, is the buſineſs, I'le go ſee whether the Coaſt in clear, and then we will contrive, with that taking up the Candle, that forc'd me to retire into my Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, not daring to hearken any more, for fear I ſhould loſe my ſelf and you alſo, for I concluded within my ſelf, that it was of you they had ſpoken, ſeeing there was no other Horſe in the Stable but yours; I preſently writ that Note you found upon the floor, which I had convey'd there under your door, and did reſolve to watch their motions narrowly that night, ſo that they ſhould miſs of an opportunity to do you miſchief, about an hour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53678:26"/> I did ſteel down the ſtairs again in the dark, to gain a further know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of their proceedings, but the Counſel was broke up, and I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd the Curate, with a long Knife, which we uſe in the Kitching, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Maſter, who carried the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle before him, this made me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that they were coming to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you, I was ſo ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>'d with fear, at this ſight, that preſently ſtealing up ſtairs again, I gave a great blow againſt you Chamber door, I as I came by it, thinking thereby to have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened you, with a deſign to have immediately run into my Chamber, and, have cry'd out Thieves and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo loud and ſo long, till I had rais'd the Neighbourhood; which I did believe would prevent them from proceeding any ſurther. But it fell out better than I expected, for the noiſe which thoſe things made which had fallen down with my puſh againſt your door, and you having diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your Piſtols upon it, gave me a juſt occaſion to cry out. Theſe noiſes had their wiſh'd effects, for preſently
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53678:26"/> after looking out of the Window, which anſwer'd into the yard, I did ſee both the Conſpirators going to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Stable, which made me conclude that they had quite given o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the attacking of you, to ſeize up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Horſe: but I ſaw them make towards the other Stable, where they were above an hour, I never took my eyes off the door till I ſaw them come out again, each having a Horſe by the Bridle, which they hung upon the Pails of the yard, preſently after my Maſter comes in, and as ſuddenly went out again with ſome Piſtols and a Gun, he open'd the yard door, they both got on Horſeback, the door was ſhut after them, and away they went. I went preſently after to ſee if the Coaſt was clear, to be more certain of your ſafety by their abſence. But dear Sir, continued <hi>Suſetta,</hi> my fears for you are not quite over yet, it is very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that having been diſappointed at home, they have taken Horſe to execute their deſigns abroad, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let me beg of you Sir, not to go directly to <hi>Paris,</hi> but get to ſome other
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:53678:27"/> place, whence you may have a guide to conduct you, to your journeys end. <hi>Le Noble,</hi> gave her a thouſand, thanks for her care of him, telling her that if he was once on Horſeback, he would not fear what they could do to him, and that he would not go a ſtep out of his way for them, with this ſhe renewed her intreaties and prayers to him, with ſo much earneſtneſs and paſſion to diſſwade him from it, that he could not but perceive that ſhe was more than ordinarily concerned for him, which made him promiſe to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low her advice, and having told her that he was confident ſhe was not what ſhe appear'd to be, it being impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to find ſo much generoſity and goodneſs in a common breaſt, ſhe with a kind of rallery, and a moſt tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing geſture told him, that if he would continue in that opinion, and honour her ſo much as to keep her in his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory; ſhe would e're long (if he would give her leave) come to him at <hi>Paris</hi> and endeavour to confirm him in that good opinion, there being ſomething in the buſineſs, which her modeſty
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53678:27"/> would not give her leave to diſcover to ſo great a ſtranger as he was, with that <hi>Le Noble</hi> aſſured her that he ſhould be the moſt ingrateful of mankind, ſhould he not be ſenſible of her ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular kindneſs to him in a more than ordinary manner, that thoſe good Offices of hers, that ſhe had done him, had for ever ingrafted her not only in his mind, but in his heart alſo, for proof whereof he moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſired, that ſhe would come to him at <hi>Paris,</hi> where ſhe ſhould find a moſt kind reception, and that he would ſerve her with his Life and Fortune, that gratitude bound him to it, and that he could never do too much for his dear preſerver, with that he gave her inſtructions how to find him, and having taken out of his pocket a Purſe full of Gold, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired her to take what ſhe pleas'd out of it, which ſhe would by no means do, pleading that ſhe had no occaſion for it, that what ſhe had done for him, was on another principle then intereſt, and that this his offers made her fear he had not ſuch fair thoughts for her, as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53678:28"/> ſhe hoped and wiſhed he might have. <hi>Le Noble</hi> ſeeing that he could not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten any money upon her, and bring the more perſwaded of her gentillity by this generous refuſal, he pul'd off a Diamond, which he had on his ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and preſented it to her, telling her by the acceptance or refuſal of it, he would know whether ſhe had as much eſteem for his perſon, as ſhe laid had compaſſion for his dangers: And with much ado he got it on her finger, and would not permit her to take it off again; ſhe at laſt, being in a manner forced to comply with his reſolution<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> told him, Sir, ſince it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to have me accept of ſo great a preſent, be pleas'd to take notice that it is upon condition you will be aſſur'd of the high eſteem I have for your perſon, and that you will be pleas'd to receive it again, when I have the honour to ſee you next. By this time it was full day, and <hi>Suſetta</hi> being call'd for, ſhe deſired <hi>Le Noble</hi> to excuſe the condition ſhe was in, being obliged to go about her buſineſs, to take, all occaſions of Suſpitions off of her
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:53678:28"/> and ſaying this, ſhe pull'd the Ring, which <hi>Le Noble</hi> had given her, off of her finger, and laying it up ſafe in her boſome, this is the Cabinet in which I ſhall preſerve your preſent, Sir, till I have the happineſs of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you again, with that making a Courteſie, and an offer to be going, <hi>Le Noble</hi> ſtept to her and having kiſs'd her, once more repcated his proteſtations of friendſhip, and ſo they parted: ſhe about her buſineſs, and <hi>Le Noble</hi> to ſee his Horſe dreſt and fed, no ſooner was the Horſe got in a readineſs, but <hi>Le Noble</hi> having given ſome money a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Servants, gets on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, and having inquired which way he ſhould get out of the Village, made his Horſe carry him towards that place. He had a deſign to ſhun the Road from that place to <hi>Paris,</hi> but his fate would carry him into it againſt his reſolution, ſo that of a ſudden he found himſelf in a certain paſſage, which had been noted to him, for a very dangerous place.</p>
               <p>It was too late to retire therefore he reſolved to truſt his fortune on the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:53678:29"/> heeles of his good horſe, if he ſhould be attacked; he had not Rid a furlongs length, upon this heat or plain, but that he eſpies two perſons coming up towards him from the wood on his left hand, he preſently concluded them, to be his two Enemies, as really they were, with that reſolving to rely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the goodneſs of his horſe, yet tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Piſtol in his hand, he begins a handſome Gallop, which in a little time, and before thoſe two could joyn him had brought him in ſight of ſome horſe men, that were coming towards him, this made him put forwards, and the two others to fall back <hi>Le Noble</hi> have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing met with the Company, they all ſtood ſtill to admire his Horſe, and one of them deſiring him to ſtop he did ſo, turns back, and ſtands ſtill they all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires his horſe, askt if it was to be ſold, to which he anſwers yes, if once he was in <hi>Paris</hi> with him, one deſired to ſee him walk, another to ſee him him Trot, and another to ſee him Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop; <hi>Le Noble</hi> perceiving, that his two ſetters were taking a Compaſs to get before him, without being known
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53678:29"/> and ſeeing alſo that thoſe he was with did whiſper to one another, and did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to come to his horſes head, which he ſtill prevented; at laſt he told them, that if they had a mind to ſee the horſe Gallop they muſt Gallop alſo, with that he ſets ſpurs to his horſe, and in a moment he had left them at ſuch a diſtance, behind him, (he continuing his ſpeed to the very gates of <hi>Paris</hi>) ſo that he never ſet eyes on them more.</p>
               <p>No ſooner was our eſcaped Traveller got ſecure within the Walls of that Great City, but he looked about and inquired for one of the beſt Inns; there he lights and ſets up his horſe, ſees him well-rub'd and Litter'd, hay given him, and then he asked for a bed for himſelf, and truly by this time, he wanted one, he calls for the Maſter of the Inn gives him his Piſtolls in charge, Orders ſomebody to go to the Coach of <hi>Roan</hi> for his Port Mantel, and ſends another meſſenger to the very other end of the Town to ſeek out the houſe of one of thoſe perſons to whom he was recommended, to deliver him a
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:53678:30"/> Letter; having given thoſe orders, he marches up to his Chamber, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing told the Servants of the houſe, that he would not be awakened nor diſturb'd till he call'd; To bed he goes, which no doubt he found very refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after all his fatigues, watchings and fears, he ſoon fell aſleep with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out rocking, and took his fill of it. The firſt thoughts that came into his head, when he awakened again, was of his dear <hi>Suſetta,</hi> he endeavoured to put them by: but it would not do, he was naturally of a Sanguine and amorous a Complexion, and that paſſion had alwayes an abſolute Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire over all the faculties of his ſoul, therefore he thought it was in vain for him to oppoſe againſt ſo great a Torrent; attendance being come, he makes inquiry after his Horſe, which he hears is very well, next demands for his Valiſe, and then asks if the Letter was delivered, his Cloak-bag is brought to him from the Coach, and news that the Meſſenger, that was ſent with the Letter, could not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly find out that houſe by the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:53678:30"/> that was upon it, this made him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to make a ſearch after it himſelf, but thinking that by that time he had ſeen his Horſe dreſs'd and fod, and himſelf dine, it would be too late in the day to begin this progreſs, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to let it alone till the next morning, and ſo repoſe himſelf, the reſt of that day.</p>
               <p>The next morning up he gets be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and dreſſes himſelf in the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſt manner he could, and ſo ſets forth in queſt of his Marchant, but to as little purpoſe, as the former Meſſenger, he had quite tired him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and was endeavouring to return to his Inn, once more looking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Superſcription of the Letter before he put it up: when there comes by him a perſon in a gentile habit, who looking alſo on the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>A Monſieur, Monſieur La Perle?</hi> Sayes he aloud, Sir, I am very glad that it is my fortune to find you here, at ſuch a time as I can ſerve you, in bringing you unto that Gentleman, my very good friend and old acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, Sir, reply'd <hi>Le Noble,</hi> in the loſs
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53678:31"/> I am at, at preſent, I ſhall make bold to accept of your kind offer, and return you many humble thanks, for you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> extroa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dinary Civillity, to a perſon ſo much a ſtranger to this part of the World as I am. Sir, no more Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements, I beſeech you, reply'd <hi>Le Noble</hi>'s new guide, the very name of that Gentleman would make me act a thouſand times more for your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: come, Sir, follow me, the way is ſomething long, intricate, and dirty, but we ſhall overcome it; with that he faces about, goes a good round pace, and <hi>Le Noble</hi> follows cloſe after, with a great fear of loſing ſo good a fortune, before he had had the full benefit of it, his guide leads him through abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of intricate by ways and Alleye, at laſt they come into a certain blind narrow ſtreet; the guide pulls a Key out of his Pocket, opens the door ſets <hi>Le No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> in formoſt, partly by Complement, partly by force, he bolts the door after him, and ſhoves him up ſtairs before him.</p>
               <p>Being come into a little dining room, he makes his Complement to <hi>Le Noble,</hi> deſires him to ſit down,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:53678:31"/> while he went into the next room to ſpeak to a friend, that he had but two words to ſay, and then he would wait on him to his Merchant, that was but cloſe by, and ſo ſteps into the next room, and pulls the door after him: mean time <hi>Le Noble</hi> ſets him down to reſt himſelf, in expectation of his Guides return, at laſt his natural Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiency makes him think the time long, and his reſtleſs humour obliges him to walk up and down the room, and to pry in every Corner, at laſt he hears a kind of noiſe, of quarrel and ſwearings, as if at ſome farther diſtance than the next room, and as he gave attention to it, of a ſudden all was huſht; this put ſome jealouſies into his mind, which had made him ſteal privately out of the houſe, but that he thought that he had heard his guide lock the door upon them, ſo ſoon as they were come in, and this increaſed the more his fears, with that he ſteps to the Window, opens it and looks out, with an intention to have call'd ſome body in but that lookt into a back yard, where he could ſee no body.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:53678:32"/>
               <p>The longer he waited the more did his fears increaſe; he ſteps to that door in which his Guide was gone, when he left him, hearkens, peeps through the key-hole, but could not ſee nor hear any body, which made him attempt to open it, but he could not, all theſe things did highly perplex him; as he was feeling round the hangings, to find out ſome other coveyance for him to get out at, he felt a hollow ſpace, he goes to the Corner of the room, takes up the hangings, and though the place was dark, he could perceive a white Cloath, as if it were upon a Table, he goes towards it, and in the dark, feels, as well as he could, what it ſhould be, at laſt, laying his hand upon ſomething like a face, very cold and clamy, he did withdraw himſelf from that place, and being come to the light found that his hands were all bloudy, at this, ſuch a Terror and Horror ſiez'd ſo ſtrongly upon his Spirits, that he was never able to give an account of what he did, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after that; but what he can remember neareſt to that bloudy fight, was that he thinks he leapt down
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:53678:32"/> ſtairs, yet was not certain, but when he came to himſelf again, he found himſelf at the bottome of the ſtairs upon the floor, and a man over him, and the ſtreet door a little open, and one of his legs between the door and the door caſe; being come to himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and ſeeing the condition he was in, he Cry'd out Murder, at which ſome paſſing by ſtopt, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired what was the matter, he that held him under anſwered preſently, that it was nothing, but a young Rogue, he had catch'd ſtealing of ſome things, they, not ſtaying ſo long as to hear <hi>Le Nobles</hi> complaints, only ſaying pay him Rogue, went their wayes. This made <hi>Le Noble,</hi> ſet open his Throat, the wider, and ſtruggle for life, which had ſo good an effect, that the next that came by were ſtopped at theſe outcryes of Murder, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned themſelves in the buſineſs, not taking the mans excuſes for currant, and perceiving by that Leg which was out of door, that it belong'd to an upparel, ſomewhat of another kind, then ſuch Rogues, as he would make
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:53678:33"/> 
                  <hi>Le Noble</hi> paſs for, do commonly wear, they forced themſelves in; no ſooner he that was upon <hi>Le Noble</hi> perceived that they would come in by force, but he left his prey, and murmering, get up ſtairs, <hi>Le Noble</hi> got up, and ſeated on the lower ſtep declared to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, that did continually increaſe, what he had found in the Chamber, that there was doubtleſs ſome body murthered in the houſe, and begg'd that he might be conveyed any where out of that place, in ſafe cuſtody till the houſe was ſearched, there was not found any perſon in it, but two dead bodies, in a Vault, joyning the Cellar, and a head, in that place that <hi>Le Noble</hi> had mentioned, but a more ſtrickt ſearch being made, even over that houſe and the neighbouring, there was found in a gutter belonging to a houſe, about the fourth from that the murtherer was in, a man that lay cloſe behind a chimney, who was diſcover'd by the prim of his hat, which gave a ſhadow upon the houſe top; he was preſently apprehended and brought were <hi>Le Nob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was detained, who preſently knew
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:53678:33"/> him to be his falſe guide; as the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers were moving in order to carry them to priſon in comes <hi>Le Nobles</hi> Merchant, who had been ſent for, ſo ſoon as <hi>Le Noble</hi> had given evidence of his innocency by divers Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, he being a perſon well known and of authority, became <hi>Le Nobles</hi> Bail, with ſome perſons preſent, that freely offered to joyn with him in <hi>Le Nobles</hi> delivery, ſo was he ſat at liberty again, and the Murtherer carried to priſon, where after he had been thrice apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Rack, the third time he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed much more than was already known, but could never be brought to diſcover any of his complices, upon which receiving ſentence, he was the next day broke alive, and ſet upon a wheel twenty four hours in publick veiw for a Terror.</p>
               <p>The Merchant having got <hi>Le Noble</hi> free, Invites him to his houſe, there to be, till he was recovered of his b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uiſes, and that he could provide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf elſewhere of private lodgings; <hi>Le Noble</hi> accepts of his civility, but firſt they go together to <hi>Le Nobles</hi> Inn,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:53678:34"/> where having diſcharged the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Hoſt told him that if he would ſell his horſe, he had a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man for it, <hi>Le Noble</hi> willing to part with his beaſt, the Gentleman was call'd, and in few words the bargain was made, and <hi>Le Noble,</hi> receiv'd a hundred Piſtols for it, with that a Coach being call'd <hi>Le Nobles</hi> things were put into it, and his Merchant and he were carried to his houſe. <hi>Le Noble,</hi> after a weeks time thought it convenient not to incommode his hoſt any longer but to retire in private lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, having taken his leave of his Merchant, and returned him many thanks for his civilities away he goes to another part of the City, where he had taken lodgings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Le Noble,</hi> during the time that he was with the Merchant, had contracted a particular friendſhip with a young man, much of his years, the Son of an Advocate of <hi>Paris,</hi> he was a good comely black man ſomewhat of a ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger make than <hi>Le Noble,</hi> and more addicted to the Bottle, than the Sheet.</p>
               <p>One day <hi>Marcine</hi> came to aquaint
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:53678:34"/> 
                  <hi>Le Noble,</hi> that his Father had ordered him to go the next morning a journey into the Country, about ſome buſineſs, which would keep him out three weeks, and that if he would go with him he ſhould be glad of his company, <hi>Le Noble</hi> having that day buſied his thoughts more than ordinarily upon the abſence of his <hi>Suſetta,</hi> which he began to think very long, this had made him out of humour and Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly, which made him tell his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion that being very much diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by their late debauches, he would make uſe of the advantage of his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, to take ſome phyſick, ſo deſired to be excuſed. <hi>Marcine</hi> gone, <hi>Le Noble</hi> locks himſelf up, in his Chamber that he might not be interrupted from giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his thoughts wholly up to his pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Suſetta,</hi> ſometime he would frame a deſign of going to ſeek after her in diſguiſe, then the danger of being known taking him off of that, he would be for ſending a meſſenger on purpuſe, with a letter to her, theſe deſigns were followed with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand more, which ſtill undid one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:53678:35"/> thus revolving in his thoughts to no effect, and it being pretty for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the night he gets him to bed, where preſently after he falls a ſleep.</p>
               <p>In the Morning news was brought him, that there was a Letter for him, he having opened his door and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it, he preſently found that it was ſubſcrib'd with the Name of his Dear <hi>Suſetta:</hi> The joy, which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived at the pleaſing ſight of that Character, made him give it a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand kiſſes, before he had the Patience to read the letter, having ſpent ſome of his fires upon that part, he had Patience to read the reſt, which he found as follows.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>DEar Sir, by a ſtrange accident I am now at a further diſtance from you then you left me, If that good opinion that you were pleaſed to entertain of me was real, or not impair'd ſince by abſence and this removal, I hope you will take the pains to come and fetch me; by your proceedings in this I ſhall know what place I hold in your thoughts and eſteem,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:53678:35"/> if you pleaſe to inquire at the <hi>Golden-Key</hi> in the High-ſtreet at <hi>Gifford,</hi> there you ſhall hear farther from your moſt obliged Servant,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SETTA.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Letter he read and cond over and over, as if he would have learn'd it by heart, at laſt thinking he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the full meaning of it, he makes a reſolution to take that journey, and with that riſes in order to ſit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of all things neceſſary, which done, the next day he gets on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, and ſets forwards towards <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His firſt dayes journy had nothing in it remarkable, but the next will afford us ſomething worth taking notice of: it happened that in the evening, he took up his lodgings at an Inn, were three or four Coaches meeting that very day, the houſe was extream full, and he coming late, and every body having ſupped, he was fore'd to beſpeak a Supper for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: mean time, while his Supper was getting ready ſeeing amongſt the reſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53678:36"/> of theſe Companies that were not yet retired into their Chambers, a pritty brisk young Woman that was very frolick, he accoſts her, and falls in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to diſcourſe with her, he found her of a very fine humour and pleaſant converſe which had made him paſs an hours time very agreeable, had it not been interrupted ſometime by an impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Husbands calls; which having not been regarded, though often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, the Husband came down ſome ſteps, and told his Wife, that if ſhe did not come preſently, he would come and fetch her; ſhe regarding it not did continue her diſcourſe with <hi>Le Noble,</hi> ſeeming as well pleaſed with his good Company and gayſome hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour as he was with hers.</p>
               <p>This ſet the goodman in ſuch a fury, that he came haſtily down in his night Cap and flippers, and taking his Wife by the Arm, he pull'd her off from her ſeat giving her ſuch a ſwing as had like to have fling her on the flour, ſaying, is this a time o'th'night to be tattling with a youngſter, ſo that, you cannot liſten to your Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:53678:36"/> when he calls you? get you up to your Chamber, or I'le ſend you up with a witneſs, ſhe recovering her ſelf, told him, that ſhe knew her own time without his advice, that if he had ſuch mind to his bed, he might go if he pleas'd, for her part ſhe had not, and that ſhe would ſtay till ſhe had a mind to it. Mean time it is very ſtrange, continued ſhe, that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forbear ſhewing your brutiſh hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour in publick, eſpecially in preſence of a Gentleman ſo civil, and of ſo pleaſing a converſation; upon this the Husband going to take her again, by the Arm, <hi>Le Noble</hi> offer'd to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in a civil manner, deſiring the Husband to forbear all harſh uſage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a perſon, who doubtleſs, had no further intentions then to paſs an hour or two in a chearful converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. At which the angry Husband, did ſnappiſhly anſwer, who are you, pray? That thus undertake to teach me? When I want a Maſter, I ſhall ſend for you, mean time meddle with own buſineſs. Go and get you a beard before you undertake
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:53678:37"/> to inſtruct a man of my years. Here his Wife interrupted him, intreating <hi>Le Noble</hi> to take no further notice of his impertinance, aſſuring him that if it were not that ſhe would detain him no longer from his Supper, ſhe would in ſpight of her Husbands ill humour, ſtay as long as ſhe pleas'd; but that ſhe did hope to recompence this loſt time the next day, if it was her good fortune to travel the ſame way. With that ſhe made him a Curteſie and retired, follow'd by her angry Husband, who did reſolve to break their meaſures, telling them, that they did reckon without their Hoſt, and that he would prevent their coming together again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Le Noble</hi> could not forbear laughing at this Jealous man's actions, though vex'd that he had ſo ſoon loſt his pretty companion. Supper being ready he fell to it, with a reſolution to have another bout with his Gentlewoman the next morning. Having ſupp'd he ask'd for a Chamber it was anſwer'd, that he might have one if he pleas'd, but that there was ne're a bed empty, the houſe being ſo full, that every bed had two in it,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:53678:37"/> except one Gentleman, that lay ſingle, that if he pleas'd to accept of part of his bed, they would go deſire the Gentleman to ſpare it him. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing late there was no remedy, ſo that <hi>Le Noble</hi> was forced to go to bed to that Gentleman, who did very civily receive him.</p>
               <p>In the dead of the night there was a great out cry heard of fire, which made all the people of the houſe to riſe to know what was the matter. <hi>Le Noble</hi> and his bed fellow amongſt the reſt, ſo did the troubleſome Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, who lay in the next Room to them. The inquiry made, it was found to be ſome ſmall harm, that an ill extinct Candle had done, which being perceiv'd by a perſon between ſleep and awake, which made him apprehend it to be worſe than it was, had cryed out fire; but that all was well again. This made every one to retire to bed again in the dark, as they had got out of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Le Noble,</hi> not long after he was in bed, heard his bed fellow ſigh and ſay, ſure never poor woman was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:53678:38"/> with ſuch a Husband as I am, at this <hi>Le Noble,</hi> conſidering where he was, did ſtretch forth his hand, that it might ſerve him in the dark inſtead of Eies, and feeling about, he laid it upon a head, which he imagin'd did belong to a woman, by the dreſs and ſliding his hand a little lower, he found by a plump, round pair of breaſts, that he was not deceived, with this he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded that this was his laſt nights com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, which he had ſo fortunately met with by miſtaking her Chamber for his; and hearing no body ſtirring, he concluded alſo that her Husband by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like miſtake, might be got to his bed, This having enboldned <hi>Le Noble,</hi> he took the liberty to embrace his bed fellow, and to whiſper in her ear, who he was, and how he had come thither, deſiring her to make no noiſe, and after ſome little buſle which ſhe made at the firſt ſurpriſal, he had time to tell her. Seeing in ſpight of her Jealous Husbands ill humour, it had pleas'd fortune to bring them in bed together, ſhe was to conclude that the fates had decreed it ſo. The rather
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:53678:38"/> too, becauſe her Husband did give them ſo fair an opportunity, by his abſence, though, he ſuppoſed, much againſt his will, that therefore ſhe was not to refuſe him, what his good fortune had ſo bountifully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon him, ſhe made ſome ſlight reſiſtance, and pleaded much the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice of the action, to which <hi>Le Noble</hi> having made ſuch anſwers as brought her to ſay, but Lord what would my Husband ſay ſhould he know it, he found by that, that the fort was yielding, therefore, after ſome more few kind words and Careſſes, he made uſe of this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, to revenge himſelf upon the Wife, of the Husbands rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to him.</p>
               <p>After ſome ſtay with her ſhe would have had <hi>Le Noble</hi> gone, but he plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he knew not whither he ſhould go, thus naked as he was, for there was no queſtion but her Husband having got to bed to his bedfellow, who he had doubtleſs taken for her, he was faſt enough till morning; and that ſo ſoon as day ſhould but ne'r
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:53678:39"/> ſo little appear, he would leave her, though to his very great regret, with that they renewed their Careſſes, ſo that they were very well ſatisfied with one anothers Company.</p>
               <p>A little before break of day, as they had concluded it, between them, <hi>Le Noble</hi> having taken leave of his kind bedfellow, he goes out of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber leaving the door open after him to ſhift for himſelf till the door of his Chamber was opened, but paſſing by it, he could not forbear trying whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was open or not, having lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the latch, the door yielded to him, he preſently gets in, and makes ſome kind of noiſe on purpoſe, that it ſhould he heard, but the firſt time falling of his expectation, he made ſuch a noiſe, that our jealous man being awakened by it, who thought pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, that it was ſome body to rob him of the jewel his Wife, or to ſteal ſomething elſe, with ſuch like thoughts, he gets out of lied, and having cry'd, <hi>qui Va la:</hi> he preſently makes towards the door, which find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cloſe ſhut, but neither lockt nor
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:53678:39"/> bolted, he opens it, and ſteps into the paſſage to ſatisfie himſelf the better, mean time <hi>Le Noble</hi> gets from the Corher of the Chimney where he had retired, faſtens the door within ſide, and preſently gets to his own bed, the affrighted man having ſearch'd up and down in the dark, and finding no body, he comes back to <hi>Le Nobles</hi> Chamber door, which find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Shut, he thought he had miſtaken it, and feeling out for another door finds that of his own Chamber, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſtanding open, as <hi>Le Noble</hi> had left it, into which being got, he ſhuts it, and goes to bed, as well ſatisfied as if he had lain there all night.</p>
               <p>Not long after day appear'd, and preſently comes one up kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>king at every Chamber door, to give notice that it was time to riſe, inſtantly the Window Curtains began to be drawn in every Chamber, and a noiſe heard, which ſtill encreaſed as paſſengers were riſing and getting ready.</p>
               <p>You may imagine that <hi>Le Noble</hi> was none of the laſt, for the haſt he
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:53678:40"/> had to bid his ſweet fellow, good mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, he gets himſelf ready, and goes out of his Chamber: our Jealous Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was the firſt that <hi>Le Noble</hi> met with in the paſſage, they bid one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good morrow, <hi>Le Noble</hi> told him, that he hoped that he was not ſo angry with him as he ſeem'd to be the night before, the Husband (whoſe anger was over) anſwer'd him, that he begg'd his pardon, but that it was her croſs humour, and obſtinacy, that had ſet him ſo out of humour: <hi>Le Noble</hi> return'd him his Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and told him that for his part, he never us'd to carry ſuch things long in his mind, for proof whereof he would deſire him and his bed-fellow, to take part of a breakfaſt, with him and his bed-fellow, the good man, who was as covetous as Jealous, (thoſe two paſſions commonly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together) return'd him ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thanks, and told him, that ſo ſoon as his Wife were ready, they would both wait on him in his Chamb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and that he would go in, to awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en her, <hi>Le Noble</hi> deſired him to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:53678:40"/> telling him it was yet early e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, that it was the Coaches Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, alwaies to call two hours for their Paſſengers before their Horſes were ready, and that peradventure ſhe had not ſlept well that night, he made anſwer, that to his knowledge, ſhe had ſlept all night like a Town Top, and not ſo much as ſtirr'd, with that he retires into his Chamber, and <hi>Le No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> goes down ſtairs into the Kitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to be-ſpeak a breakfaſt, ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to his Chamber again, he found his Chamber fellow riſing, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bid him good morrow, he return'd him thanks for his kindneſs, when he was deſtitute of a bed, after ſome more Complements of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, according to the French cuſtome, what ſhall we have for breakfaſt, ſayes the Gentleman. Sir, replyed <hi>Le Noble,</hi> I have juſt now t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ken care for that, and I hope, you will pleaſe to accept of a bit with me, and thoſe perſons that lye in the next Room: After the thanks return'd, their diſcourſe, while they were dreſſing, was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the accident that had fallen out that
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:53678:41"/> night by fire, which might have been of very evil conſequence, near ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtables, had it not been ſo happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prevented, with that they reflected on an hundred accidents that are apt to befal Travellers, not only in their Inns, but on the Rode alſo, to which was added the churliſh and dogged humours of Coachmen, and they concluded, with the unreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Hoſts in their reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>By this time they were ready, and <hi>Le Noble</hi> hearing the Gentlewomans voyce, after the French airy manner which he had naturally, <hi>Bonjour, Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jour, Madamoiſelle,</hi> ſayes he aloud, what is it not breakfaſt time with you yet? I fear you have not had a good nights reſt, continued he, you ſpeak ſo faintly this morning, to which ſhe anſwered, that ſhe never had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> more pleaſant night, and ſuch reſt as ſhe wiſh'd ſhe might enjoy often; which ſhe believ'd was caus'd partly by her ſitting up late, and the ſatisfaction which ſhe had laſt night in his agreeable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, for proof whereof, ſhe was
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:53678:41"/> almoſt dreſs'd, and ready to take a good ſhare of that breakfaſt, which her Husband had inform'd her that he had invited them unto. By that, both the Companies being ready, they met in the paſſage, where they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new'd their diſcourſe, in a pleaſant way of raillery upon the laſt nights acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and the diſorder it would have ſet them all in, had it continued long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, every one giving his ſenſe upon it, according to his fancy, with this a Servant comes up, to know where they would have the Cloath laid, they not agreeing in whoſe Chamber, they all went down into the Parler, where they found their breakfaſt waiting for them, preſently they fell to it, and forks being wanting, the Gentlewoman de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired her Husband to fetch down hers and her Spoon, which ſhe commonly carryed with her, when ſhe Travell'd, which the Husband did accordingly, they had in that Interval, a little more leaſure to contemplate one another, by day light, though amorous glances, had not been wanting between them, all the while before, ſome bluſhes, which
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:53678:42"/> the remembrance of their nights converſation rais'd upon the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Cheeks, added much grace to her natural beauty, ſo that our Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller, was infinitely taken with it, preſently the Husband returnes, and they fell to eat, with as good an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite as Travellers uſe to have: one of the queſtions, amongſt their other diſcourſe, was which way each per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon did Travel, by the anſwers, <hi>Le No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> finding that he ſhould ſoon be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to part from his dear bed-fellow ſaid, I am extreamly ſorry, that I muſt part ſo ſoon from ſo good a bed-fellow, as I have had to night, to whom I muſt remain infinitely obliged for his kind reception of me in the bed, when I was deſtitute of one, all the hopes that I have to requite it, is by being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd where I might have the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to kiſs his hands hereafter; that, reply'd the Lady, is ſo ſmall a kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as I believe the Gentleman will hardly refuſe; yea, Madam, reply'd the Gentleman, he may command me in things of greater conſequence, he now giving me the advantage, in the hopes
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:53678:42"/> of injoying hereafter, more of his gay humour, as <hi>Le Noble</hi> was going to reply, the Lady ſaid in a merry accent, juſt ſo would I have anſwer'd, I'le aſſure you, Sir, onely with this addition, that though there were never ſo many beds empty, he ſhould afford me the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his Company in bed with me, the good Husband, who all this while had laid about him, ſo that he could not ſpare time to ſpeak one word, then ſaid, you are very forward Wife; if you would have anſwer'd ſo, 'tis like that this Gentleman, would not be of your humour, except he were of your Sex alſo, and therefore you might have left out that Clauſe, though the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands words had been meant of this Gentleman, yet <hi>Le Noble</hi> took upon him, to anſwer thus, ſince that by this ſmall interview, we may have ſome knowledge of one another, we may hereafter prove very good bed-fellows, and recompence the time we loſt this night, Sir, I could anſwer you again, though you did not addreſs your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to me, but that I have a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, of ſo ſtrange a humour, that I
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:53678:43"/> muſt not ſpeak. Pray, ſpeak your belly full, reply'd the Husband, I'le not hinder you, but why ſhould you undertake to ſpeak another perſons conceptions? <hi>Le Noble,</hi> to break off their Jarring began a good health to the Company, and preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Coachman came in to tell them that he was ready: This made them all riſe and prepare to be going, but <hi>Le Noble</hi> deſirous to prolong the time ſo long as he could, gave the Coachman ſomething in private, and bad him go drink a pot of Wine upon his ſcore: This made him tractable for one half hour longer thou he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe would have been. Mean time the Husband and the Gentleman were gone to get their things in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which gave <hi>Le Noble</hi> ſome time to ſpeak in private to his bed-fellow, Madam, ſaid he, ſhall I not be made ſo happy, as to know where I may here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after have the happineſs to kiſs your hands, and aſſure you of the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation of my moſt humble ſervices? Yes, Sir, reply'd the Lady, and to let you ſee, that I am as deſirous of ſeeing you
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:53678:43"/> where; pray Sir accept of theſe Tab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, which will inform you at lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, with that ſhe pulling a Table<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>book from her pocket, at which there was faſtened a Diamond Ring, ſhe preſented it to him in a moſt obliging manner; adding that ſhe would gueſs at the eſteem he had for her by his dilligence in rendering her a viſit: <hi>Le Noble,</hi> was going to reply, when the Husband came in followed by a Servant that carried the baggage, this broke off their diſcourſe, and the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman went to ſee whether her Husband had left any thing behind. The Coachmans bawling did preſently bring her back again, and <hi>Le Noble</hi> waiting on her to the Coach, took leave of her, of her Husband, and of the other Gentleman alſo, leaving them going towards <hi>Paris,</hi> and he preſently after, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aking horſe for <hi>Gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He had not patience to ſtay till ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting time to look on the preſent which he had received from his kind bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow at parting, but as he was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Road he pulls the Tablets out
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:53678:44"/> of his Pocket, in which he found in every leaſe nothing but <hi>Lauretta</hi> on it all over, except one leafe which had on one ſide this writ,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>When on theſe Tablets you my name do find,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe favours you received, bear in your mind,</l>
                  <l>And let this Ring, when on your finger worne.</l>
                  <l>Bring in you thoughts, what lately you have ſworn, <hi>To yours Lauretta.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>And on the other ſide of the ſame leafe he found this writ.</p>
               <p>If ever you think me worthy of a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, come to the next door of the three <hi>Kings,</hi> in <hi>Mercers</hi> ſtreet at <hi>Lyons;</hi> where you will find me continually regreting the Long abſence of my moſt dear bedfellow with all the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row imaginable.</p>
               <p>Having read this he wondred that ſo much ſhould be pen'd in ſo little time, not knowing when ſhe could have done it: Which he concluded muſt of neceſſity be that which ſhe commonly us'd to employ every morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in her devotions; having unty'd the Ring, he put it on his finger, with
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:53678:44"/> ſome thoughts to be further acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Lady after his return to <hi>Paris.</hi> And then his dear <hi>Suſetta</hi> coming in his mind, that diverted him from any further thoughts of the Lady for the preſent.</p>
               <p>The impatiency to be at his jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies end made him haſten to his horſe, on which being got he that day came to <hi>Giffors,</hi> where having found out the ſigne of the Golden <hi>Key,</hi> he ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there after a certain Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who had ſent to him to meet her there. The Maſter of the Inn made anſwer, that there had been a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man there, that had been gone from thence two dayes ſince, and had left a Letter to be delivered to a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that ſhould come to inquire after a Woman, that by the Character the Gentleman had left, it could be none but him, and ſo gave <hi>Le Noble</hi> a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in which he found what followes,
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <p>DEar, Sir, a buſineſs of importance forcing me hence, at an hours warning, is the cauſe I have not waited here, till you came. But I hope you will
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:53678:45"/> not refuſe, after your long journey, to ride half a dozen Miles further, where moſt certainly you will find, your moſt infinitely obliged Servant.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>S.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>And caſting his eye a little lower he found this poſtcript.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I hope you know the Character ſo well as to be ſatisfied with one letter, for the whole name. Ask at the Inn for one</hi> Megerlain <hi>who ſhall be your Guide, make what haſt you can, the buſineſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He needed no more to haſten his departure, and having got the fellow ready, they ſet forwards.</p>
               <p>They were not half a mile out of Town; when <hi>Le Nobles</hi> Guide met with one he knew, that was riding with all ſpeed to the Town for a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary to make his Maſters Will, who was near death.</p>
               <p>This Tale ſet the Guide into ſuch a fit of Crying and ſobbing, that <hi>Le Noble</hi> could not forbear asking him what the Devil he ayl'd? Ah! Sir re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the fellow, he was the beſt
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:53678:45"/> Maſter that ever whipt Shool-boy, or taught ſpelling: then howling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain as if he were at an Iriſh fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, methinks I ſee him ſtill, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued he, how he would call to me, <hi>Megerlain</hi> go fetch me three Eggs (Oh, he lov'd them dearly) hoyl them for my breakfaſt, and when I have done with, them, thou ſhalt have the remainder to make thee ſome ſcollards Eggs for thy dinner. But now he's gone, and I ſhall be no more call'd to look his head, Ah! that head, that head in which ſo many fine things were Cubbord up, well but he's gone, or at leaſt juſt going. <hi>Le Noble</hi> weary of this fellows im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent paſſion, bid him hold his peace, that ſurely he was not dead yet, or that a Notary had not been ſent for. Ah, Sir, reply'd the fellow, you are come too late; I fear, that it may well be ſaid of you, after death the Phyſitian, my Maſter muſt be dead, or he would never have ſent for a Notary, he lov'd his money too well, to my knowledge, to make his Will before he were certain that he were dead, eſpecially when he knew
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:53678:46"/> that ſo rare a Phyſitian as you was on the way to viſit him, I am ſure you had been welcome, you that are the charitable Doctor, who take no money of any body. Ah? He lov'd thoſe kind of good perſons, that would not be greedily Bawling after their Fees, were they Lawyers, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians, or of any profeſſion, but he is gone, and the young Gentleman that I left with him, has ſent for you in vain, well it is done, and when grim death as once ſaid I'le have thee, 'tis in vain to cry, hold Coachman: for you know, Sir, needs muſt go that the Devil drives, as the Proverh ſayes, and as another learned ſaying of his was; the Devil take the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, he is gone and we muſt follow after him. Thus running his divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſo faſt, that <hi>Le Noble</hi> had not time to put in a word, at laſt they came to the place, where <hi>Le Noble.</hi> was brought into a Chamber, in which preſently after, a young Gentleman came, who having ſhut the door af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, running to <hi>Le Noble,</hi> and flinging himſelf about his neck. Take
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:53678:46"/> your <hi>Suſetta</hi> ſaid he, Sir, by this you have deſerv'd her: At this <hi>Le Noble</hi> ſteping back, ſo ſoon as as he was freed of the embraces, knew preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that it was his dear <hi>Suſetta,</hi> in mans apparel, with that renewing their embraces and carreſſes, after a pauſe, <hi>Suſetta</hi> told him that he was preſently to appear very grave, and act the part of a Phyſitian, that ſhe had no time to give him further In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions at preſent, but deſired him to follow her, where that he would be ſuddenly inform'd; with that they both went from that room to the ſick mans Chamber, where there was no other light, but what a farthing watch Candle did afford, ſo that <hi>Le Noble</hi> was ſome time before he could make uſe of his eye ſight. At laſt <hi>Suſetta</hi> having brought <hi>Le Noble</hi> to the bedſide, and convey'd his hand upon the ſickmans arm, I pray, Sir, ſaid ſhe, feel his Pulſe, and tell me what hopes I may have, and as you ever were my very good friend, be pleas'd to uſe the beſt of your skill, for the recovery of my dear Uncle, who I
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:53678:47"/> aſſure you, I ſhall not long ſurvive, if it is decreed he muſt now dye, with that ſhe ſeem'd to weep moſt bitterly. The poor ſick Creature, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had clear'd his Throat of ſome troubleſome Phlegm; which barrica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d up his ſpeech, ſpoke in a low voice as follows: my Dear heart, I charge thee by our Loves, and by that power, I ſhould have had over thee, if it had pleas'd the Heavens to have let me live, that thou grieve not for me, I die contented now that I am aſſured of thy real affections, but I beg of thee, that thou wouldſt live to enjoy all that I have, which I leave thee, I find it is too late, to wait for a Notary, therefore all you that are preſent here, take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, continued he, with a loud voice, that I give all that I have to this perſon my Nephew, unto whom I give theſe my Keys, and I here in the preſence of you all, declare her my heir, with that he reached forth his arm to <hi>Suſetta,</hi> and dropt a bunch of Keys into her hand, and there Pauſing a while for a little breath,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:53678:47"/> they could hear ſome of thoſe perſons that were in the Chamber ſay, now for certain he is going, for he raves, and takes his kinſman for a woman, alaſs, poor man, peace be with his ſoul, a while after he thus began again, if there is any body in this houſe that can write, let them ſet down what I have ſaid, and I will ſigne it, as well as I can, and let all thoſe that have heard me, and that ſhall ſee me ſigne it, witneſs it with their hands; then after another little pauſe, <hi>Suſetta,</hi> ſayes he, give me thy hand, <hi>Suſetta</hi> having laid her hand into his, when I am gone, remember me, and pray, whoſoever writes my Will, let him make haſt, for I have not long to ſtay I find: <hi>Suſetta</hi> held her handker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheif before her eyes all this while, as if ſhe wept, and forcing a ſob from her breaſt, ſigh not, nor grieve for me ſaid the ſick man; by this time <hi>Le Noble,</hi> who had taken upon him to write the will, had made an end, it was preſently brought to the dying man with a pen and ink, who had no ſooner ſet his hand to it, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t turning
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:53678:48"/> on one ſide, cryed farewel <hi>Suſ.</hi> and ſo gave up the Ghoſt, preſently there was a whining cry in the room, which <hi>Le Noble</hi> did immediately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt, by preſenting to each of them the Will, to ſet their marks to, for there was not one could read nor write, but the Prieſt, who having of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiated to the ſick man in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was gone; preſently after <hi>Le No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> and <hi>Suſetta</hi> were forced to go into another room, to be out of the hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous noiſe, that <hi>Magerlain</hi> was making for the Death of his Maſter: <hi>Suſetta</hi> gave order for all things for his buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, which was performed the next day, after which all the perſons of the houſe, acknowledging her as a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew and heir to the deceas'd, they apply'd themſelves to her for their payments, and <hi>Suſetta</hi> having that day diſcharged the houſe alſo ſhe gave unto <hi>Megetlain</hi> all that was his Maſters, which was of no great conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quence, and ſo diſmiſs'd him, reſerving to her ſelf one little Trunk in which ſhe had locked up all the writings, the mony <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat was left and ſome other things of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:53678:48"/> value which they caus'd to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey'd to the next Market Town to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Paris,</hi> where they followed immediately after.</p>
               <p>Here they began to breath, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate one another, and renew their Careſſes, <hi>Le Noble</hi> ſaying to <hi>Suſetta</hi> that by his diligence he had made to obey her at the firſt ſummons he hoped ſhe was convinced of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to her, and aſſured her, that all he had proteſted was real, of which he would give her further proofs, when ever ſhe ſhould deſire it, my dear <hi>Le Noble,</hi> reply'd <hi>Suſetta,</hi> I am ſo well ſatisfied in all reſpects, that I give my ſelf wholly up to you, to do what you pleaſe with me, one thing I ſhall only deſire of you; <hi>Le Noble,</hi> having asked her what it was, ſhe made anſwer, that ſhe beg'd of him, that he would continue his love to her, and not forſake her. Nay, if you begin to Article once, reply'd <hi>Le Noble</hi> merrily, let me make one alſo, and that ſhall be, that as you deſire I ſhould alwayes continue in my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to you, which I grant you, you
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:53678:49"/> ſhould never talk of that formal thing call'd Marriage, which you muſt grant me; tis done, anſwer'd <hi>Suſetta,</hi> and add to this continued ſhe, that all our goods ſhall be in common; done ſaid <hi>Le Noble,</hi> and let me add, contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he, that we ſhall inſeparably live to gether, and run the ſame fortune; done ſaid, <hi>Suſetta,</hi> and I will conclude with this that we may not be bedfellows till we arrive at <hi>Paris,</hi> where I will dreſs me like a bride, to appear the more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeably to you; mean time I ſhall be contented with theſe womens courſe dreſs; both cry'd <hi>Amen,</hi> and having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terchangably ſeal'd thoſe Articles, with kiſſes upon their Cheeks, lips, and hands; now my dear <hi>Le Noble,</hi> ſaid <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetta,</hi> I do preſent thee here with all that I am Miſtreſs of, and all that thou canſt command from her, who is thy moſt affectionate Miſtreſs <hi>Suſetta,</hi> with that ſhe pull'd a great ſilk Purſe out of her pocket, and having given it him, here take all, continued ſhe, nay me and all, ſo giving it him, ſhe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t her ſelf in his lap, and ſlung her armes about him, after <hi>Le Noble</hi> had given her a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:53678:49"/> kiſſes, and as many embraces, ſhe ſaying ſhe came not emptyhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him, and that ſhe had reſerv'd nothing to her own particular uſe; but the Ring he had given her, as the firſt pledge of his affections; I ſhould take it ill of thee, <hi>Suſetta,</hi> ſaid he, if thou ſhouldſt part with that on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny terms; but le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me ſee, what thou haſt given me here, 'tis very heavy? Nay 'tis worth your peruſal, I aſſure you, ſaid <hi>Suſetta,</hi> with that <hi>Le Noble</hi> Empties the Purſe into his Hat, which he found was fill'd with Gold and a very little ſilver with it, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which was <hi>Matthew Clods</hi> Ring. This Gold I would have you keep againſt a pinch, the Silver ſaid <hi>Suſetta</hi> will help to ſerve our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſions, and it comes very ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably. I'le aſſure thee Girl, ſaid <hi>Le Noble,</hi> for I have been extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant ſince I ſee thee laſt; hold ſaid ſhe, firſt let me give full imformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and then I will have an account of the time you have ſpent in <hi>Paris</hi> ſince you left me, here is a hundred and fifty Piſtols, continued ſhe, and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:53678:50"/> theſe papers are Bills of Exchange up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſight for eight hundred more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides half an years intereſt, which will be due, by that time we get to <hi>Paris?</hi> How Eight hundred, ſaid <hi>Le Noble,</hi> nine hundred and fifty, beſides the Silver, the intereſt, and this Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Ring? thou art a Queen? Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, what ſhall we do with all this money? Even be merry, make much of our ſelves, and love one another, reply'd <hi>Suſetta:</hi> thou haſt ſurpris'd me, ſaid <hi>Le Noble,</hi> but I prithy now give me a full account, how thou cameſt by all this, I know that thy deceaſed gallant did give it thee in his Will and Teſtament, thou haſt likewiſe inform'd me of ſome other particulars: But I beg of thee while we reſt our ſelves here, that thou wouldſt give me a full account of thy Life, and to induce her the more to it, he told her of his ſtrange ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures at <hi>Paris</hi> and upon the Rode, with his odd Maſcarading, which highly pleas'd her humour, being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways very much taken with any thing that was rare and ſingular: after
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:53678:50"/> which, he having once more deſired the Relation of her Story, ſhe thus began.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Hiſtory of S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SETTA.</head>
               <p>I was born ſome eighteen years ſince in the City of <hi>Roan</hi> in <hi>Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> my Father was a Prieſt, who hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a pritty young woman to his houſe ſervant, he took a fancy to to her, and ſo between them I was Got, my Mother ſome time after I came into the World, took the pains to go out of it; and the goodman, my Father, what with ſorrow for the loſs of his dear <hi>Suſanna</hi> (ſo was my Mother call'd) and partly to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all occaſions of talk, which had been but too loud amongſt the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood concerning them two, he took to him a good old woman, who has ever ſince ſerv'd to look to his houſe, and dreſs his Meat; I was baptiſed <hi>Suſetta,</hi> in remembrance of my Mother, and preſently after ſent to <hi>Cane,</hi> to be Nurs'd up by a Siſter of my Fathers, who took a ſpecial care of me, according to the orders ſhe had receiv'd from the good Prieſt,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:53678:51"/> he had a ſingular love for me, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the only Child that he ever had, though ſome are of another opinion, who ſay, that the good Prieſt, not being able to give my Mother as much as ſhe expected, ſhe call'd a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he aſſiſtance, who took the pains to make me: But let that paſs, the good Prieſt being pleas'd to own me for his Daughter, in gratitude I muſt acknowledge him for my Father. I was not quite ſeven years old, when being impatient to live any longer without the continual ſight of me, ſent for me home, he did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs all the kindneſs imaginable to me, and when I was grown up to it, ſet me to learn all the pritty things and Exerciſes that young Maids uſe, and ever after, paſſing all over <hi>Roan</hi> for his Siſters Daughter, I call'd him my Uncle and he me his Neece: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was quite fifteen, I had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd agreeable in the Eyes of divers perſons, whom would fain have been nibbling. But the good man, who ever carried a watchful eye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me, would put them all by; ſome
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:53678:51"/> he thought too wild, others too rich, ſome again too poor, and others too ſober; yet gueſſing by himſelf, and my Mothers conſtitutions of what temper I might be, and remembring that Cat will to kind, he endeavour'd to find out a fit match to rid his hands of me, ſo ſoon as he could, knowing that a Maid at fifteen is the moſt difficult thing in the World to be kept, reſolving if he once met with a man to his mind, to beſtow me upon him, with that he had ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, during his forty years ſervice in the Church. Amongſt the reſt of my Suiters, for I had many and of all ſorts, there was one that the good man did approve of; he was an ill bred Chip of an rough hewen block: And doubtleſs, directly deſcended from the ancient family of the Clowns, and nearly allied to that of the <hi>La Fooles:</hi> But he was very rich, and a thriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man, and conſequently eſteem'd a very fit match for me, by my good Unkle, who did not conſider that it was very reaſonable if he would cut that I ſhould chooſe, however I was of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:53678:52"/> that mind, and I behav'd my ſelf ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly: At that time, there was alſo upon the ranks my lately deceas'd Lover, who ſtood ſtoutly in Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition with my Clown, for though the laſt was prefer'd; yet the Old man did admit of him alſo, to the excluſion of all other pretenders.</p>
               <p>He was a Scotchman by Birth, a ſhirk by Education, a Pedant by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, a Beaſt in manners, and a Knave by nature. His Parents it was thought were a Merchant, ſuch a one as I have been told, Sell Cloth up and down the ſtreets in <hi>England,</hi> and a Trul, that a Tinker had caſt off, for her two inſeparable qualities, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continency and drunkenneſs, was his Mother, his name was <hi>Sawndy.</hi> But, as once he told me for brevity ſake, he was call'd <hi>Bar-tho-lo-me-us.</hi> From an under-Uſher that taught boyes to ſpell, he had in twenty eight years time attained to the Supremacy of a Writing-School. And through his miſerable Covetouſneſs, and hard Griping, and half ſtarving of his Boarders, he had ſcrap'd together
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:53678:52"/> all that we are now owners of.</p>
               <p>Now I have given you an exact ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of my two Lovers, give me leave to acquaint you with their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wooing alſo.</p>
               <p>My Clown, who was of a baſhful nature, would frequently ſit half a day by me, and not ſpeak a word; and for fear I ſhould divert him from that agreeable ſilence, neither would I ſay any thing to him, nor ſo much is look towards him, though his eyes were continually fixed upon me.</p>
               <p>On a day, after he had ſate ſome four hours before me, at a pritty di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> laſt his Hat dropt at his feet, he being faſt aſleep, I ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that, went haſtily out of the Room, and locked the door after me, for I was not ſo hard hearted as to awaken him from ſo ſweet a ſleep, as ſome other more unkind would have done. But on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, making the leaſt noiſe I could, I retired, and there I left him enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his agreeable dreams, and went my wayes with the Key of the Room, to paſs the Evening with a young
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:53678:53"/> ſhe companion of mine, our very next neighbour: We were ſitting very attentively at our works, when there came in a couple more of young Maidens with an intention to be merry, while every one was asking; what we ſhould do, and how we ſhould paſs away our time: It came into my head that my ſleeping Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, who I had left without fire or Candle, might be a fit ſubject for our nights recreation, with that I caſt about within me, how I ſhould contrive it, and having thought on ſomething, I propos'd to the reſt, that if they would joyn with me in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign I had, it would afford them ſufficiency of Mirth, for to paſs that Evening away, at the coſt of one of my Lovers, who I had lockt up in a Chamber, where he was fallen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep.</p>
               <p>Thoſe three, mad Wenches that lov'd roguery as well as I did, that is with all their hearts, did preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly embrace the propoſition, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one lent their invention to the compoſing of this frolick. By good
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:53678:53"/> fortune, the good Prieſt my Unkle, being gone Supper to a friends houſe, we had more liberty and conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncy to act our Sport, therefore we preſently went all to our houſe, taking along with us an overgrown Baboon, that was very tame and gentle, and a Cat alſo; we got all into a Parlour joyning the Room my Lover was in, whence we could hear him ſnore as if for a wager, having got all things that was thought neceſſary to carry our deſign in a readineſs, we begun to prepare. Two of my Companions were dreſſing the Baboon all in white fixing a Candle in his head, while my other Comrade and my ſelf, were faſtening of Walnut ſhells, on the Cats Claws with Pitch, rubbing her back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide with Ginger, and ſetting a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ruff about her neck. This done, I went to open the door, while the others brought with them the Baboon and the Cat, they were preſently let looſe in the ſleepers Room, after we had placed a piece of ſmall ſearing Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in one of the Corners of the Chimney, which gave but a very
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:53678:54"/> ſmall light, the door being ſhut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, we ſtood at the Window with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, as much conceal'd as we could in expectation of the event, we had no ſooner poſted our ſelves, but we heard a moſt fearful ratling, which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Baboon made running after the Cat, our Chears, Tables, Cupboards, and all things in the Room, dragging his long Chain after him, with a moſt hideous noiſe, and the Cat did make ſuch ſlidings upon the boards, who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe would endeavour to ſhun the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boon, as were very pleaſant, and ſometimes leaping againſt ſhe hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to get out of the enemies reach, it would make ſuch an odd kind of noiſe, when it fell down again upon the Nut ſhells, that it preſently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened my poor ſlumbering Lover: But had you ſeen him, when yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſleep and wake, he did but half diſcern, through the dim light in the Chimney (for that upon the Baboons head was extinguiſht) what a fear ſeiz'd him, you would have laught your fill, he ſtair'd, his Hairs ſtood an end, his Face as pale as aſhes, and all his
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:53678:54"/> Limbs as ſtiff, as if he had been fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen to death. But at laſt, the Cat being hard put to it, and forc'd for its ſafety to leap into the Lovers lap, the Baboon got immediately after it upon his ſhoulders, ſtill as he run round after the Cat, winding his Chain about this poor Lovers neck, and then on a ſudden giving it a twich as he was jumping down after the Cat, that had chang'd her quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, he pull'd the Lover down af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> him, all along upon the ground tugging with all his ſtrength to get looſe, and our Lover holding the Chain, with both his hands to prevent ſtrangling, who at laſt cryed out, good ſweet Maſter Devil, forgive me this time and let me looſe again, and if ever I offer to think or dream of woman again, you ſhall do with me what you pleaſe, while he was with theſe and ſuch like humble ſupplications, begging of the Devil for Life, the Baboon by force and violent ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rugling, having broke his Chain retir'd to the Corner of the Chimney near the Candle, and our
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:53678:55"/> Lover thinking that the Devil had done this at his requeſt, took the boldneſs to ſit up, and then turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon his knees, ſtill having the Chain about his neck, he return'd his Devilſhip his moſt humble thanks, for his kind deſiſting, from torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, promiſing him faithfully that if he ever he got on earth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, he would never think more of Miſtreſs <hi>Suſetta,</hi> for whom he did believe all this evil had befallen him; which was the more excuſable in him added he, by reaſon that it was not of his own ſeeking, but of her Unkles, who would not let him be quiet, but ſtill put him on to make Love to his Neece, thus was he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on with his excuſes to his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd Devil, when the Baboon hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perceiv'd the Cat behind our Lover, made towards him with a great deal of eagerneſs; the Cat who had ſound that place its beſt refuge, being loth to quit that poſt, ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to him, did dodge round our Lover, and his Adverſary after him, which ſet our Lover in ſuch a
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:53678:55"/> fright, that he run up and down the Room over all he met in his way, and crying but, murther, Devils, help, as loud as he could roar, tumbling in the dark over Chairs and Stools, till at laſt being quite ſpent, he fell down on a ſudden, crying out that he was dead.</p>
               <p>That word, and we ſeeing him lie without motion, did ſet us all in ſome apprehenſion that the fool might die with fear: Therefore I went and open'd the door where he lay, and preſently we ſtole all away, to give him leave to do ſo likewiſe. The door of the Chamber had not been long open, when the Cat run out of it into the Yard, from whence ſhe crept into a ſmall hole, where the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boon, who had followed her cloſe, at the Heels, was forc'd to leave off his Chaſe, the noiſe that thoſe two Creatures had made in the Yard, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been heard by the old woman (who had not heard any thing of that, which had been made in the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, becauſe it was at a further diſtance, and the door and Windows ſhut) made haſte down ſtairs, to ſee what
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:53678:56"/> was the matter, at which we all ran out of the houſe, into that from whence we came, and the Baboon after us: As we paſs'd by the Window, we hear'd our poor Lover groan, and ſay, I wonder whether I am dead or no, this ſet us out of fears, ſo that we went, and ſate us down up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a bench, that was before our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours door, laughing moſt heartily at the trick we had put upon my Lover; which, I hope, would deter him from e're coming more near our door.</p>
               <p>We had but juſt undreſs'd the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boon and let him in, when my Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle came by from his Company, with whom he had ſupp'd and drank'd ſo plentifully, that he paſs'd by and did not know me. But went into his houſe and pull'd the door after him; being come into the Yard he over heard this Dialogue, which paſs'd between the Lover and the Old wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which I alſo heard hearkening at the Window of the ſtreet.</p>
               <p>The Old woman, who had been ſearching about to know what was the cauſe of that noiſe, was come at laſt to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:53678:56"/> the Chamber door, where our Lover lay on the floor, in the dark, amongſt a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of tumbled Chairs, Stools, Cuſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Carpets: She having heard him fetch a deep ſigh, <hi>Jeſu Maria,</hi> whoſe there, ſaid ſhe; our Lover hearing a humane voyce, with ſuch a pious van-guard to its interrogation, he pluck'd up a little heart, and thus made anſwer, <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> it is I, and who in the name of all the ſhe Saints in Heaven are you, continued the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; in the Name of all the he Saints on Earth, I am <hi>Matthew Clod,</hi> that have been tormented in Hell all this Night, by two furious Devils, which have but very lately left me, in a moſt ſad pickle, for Heavens ſake con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he, ſay all the <hi>Kyry's,</hi> you know, and all the <hi>Aves</hi> for my ſoul, for though I think this place is too cold to be Hell, yet I believe I am in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory: in Purgatory, reply'd the Old woman, Heavens forbid that my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters houſe were a Purgotary, why do you not ſee that you are in the very Room, in which you uſe to make Love to one <hi>Suſetta.</hi> Oh ſpeak not a
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:53678:57"/> word more of that I beſeech you, reply'd my Lover, leaſt that the Devils return and torment me again. Why ſure, you are mad ſaid the woman, ſo coming nearer him with the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, the tippled Prieſt, mean time, ſtole up to his Chamber with an intention to clear his houſe from thoſe evil ſpirits. The old woman having ſeen what a confuſion was in the room, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held poor <hi>Matthews</hi> face all bloody. I think the Devils have been here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, ſaid ſhe, Lord what a ſtink they have left behind them? But in the name of wonder, how came you here, at this time o'th' night? Why truly reply'd <hi>Matthew,</hi> all that I know of it is, that I being faſt aſleep in bed at home, the Devils have drag'd me hither with this Chain about my neck, and having brought me into this dark room, where I uſe to gaze on <hi>Suſetta,</hi> theſe cruel Devils, or Spirits, I know not which, but one of the two I am ſure of, have ſet me in this pickle, and all the things thus confuſedly ſcattered about the room. But now you talk of our <hi>Suſetta</hi> where is ſhe, ſaid the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:53678:57"/> old woman; pray Heaven ſhe be ſafe, at this the Cat with the Wallnut ſhels having been diſturb'd from its reſt by the Prieſt, who took it for a Devil by the noiſe it made, and the ruff a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout its neck, came for refuge into that room again, at which poor <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> more affrighted than ever, cry'd out as loud as ever he could, the Devil is come again, the old woman hearing and ſeeing the Cat in that dreſs, in her fright took it for no leſs then an Imp, which made her run haſtily out of the Chamber, juſt as her Maſter was running into it, in purſuit of the Cat, they run ſo furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly againſt one another, that they both threw themſelves backwards up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the floor; the poor woman with her fright and her fall, was in a ſound, and the poor Prieſt very much indamag'd, but he being pot valliant, and by good fortune his hollowed Candle, which he had in his hand having kept light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, beſides all his holy attire, the holy water, the Croſs, and the book of Exorciſm, which he had about him, in which things he put great confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence;
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:53678:58"/> all theſe things; I ſay, did high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſence him againſt thoſe evils Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits that did haunt his houſe, he haſtily aroſe to proceed forward, the Prieſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing got into the Room, and having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held all this confuſion, he began his Exorciſm. The old woman lying all this while on her back, with her Cloaths half up, the Candle in her hand, <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> taking the Prieſt for an Illuſion crying out, Murther, the Devils, more Spirits come to torment me, not once daring to move from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the middle of the Chair frame, where he was got, I having had my fill of laughing, I went to the door which I found but latcht, having got in, and advanced ſo far as the door of the Chamber, I receiv'd a good flap on the Chaps, which my Unkle gave me with his Holy water ſprinkling, he aſſuredly taking me for another Spirit than I was, at this <hi>Matthew</hi> fell a roaring worſe than ever, crying out? Oh, and is the chief Devil come hither alſo, now there's no hopes left, I am dead, I am dead, and ſo lay gron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: by this time the Prieſt was mumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:53678:58"/> of his Charmes, and now and then throwing of hollowed water at me, I adventured to ask him what was the matter, making my ſelf the greateſt ſtranger to all this that could be, he continued his muttering without an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerings, I had a good mind once to to have pull'd him by the Arm, but then again I durſt not, when I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the blow he had given me, leaſt I ſhould bring ſome further miſcheife upon my ſelf; I perceiving that I could do no good there; I came to the old woman again, I took her up, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured her, that I was no Apparition, but the moſt real <hi>Suſetta,</hi> at laſt I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded her to go up with me in my Chamber, where after I had told her, that all this confuſion had happened through a trick, that I and ſome of my Companions had put on <hi>Matthew,</hi> ſhe having put me to bed, went down ſtaires again, to undeceive the reſt.</p>
               <p>She found them in the ſame poſture that we had left them in, ſo ſoon as ſhe came near my Unkle he beſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led her with holy water, of which he was very laviſh, at which ſhe ſaid to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:53678:59"/> him come, come, tis time to leave off your Conjurings, and you (turning towards <hi>Matthew</hi>) your folly, you may even thank that unlucky patch <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetta</hi> for all this, ſhe it was, that brought in all thoſe Devils which have ſo affrighted you both, to which the Prieſt with a deal of wrath and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, made this reply avoyd thou Satanneſs, that woulds delude me, and this poor miſerable poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed wretch, pointing at <hi>Matthew,</hi> I know thou art a deluding Devil, and I will ſend thee from me, with that he flung all the holy water he had left, in the old womans face, which ſhe took ſo ill from him, that ſaying the Devil take you both, ſhe went her wayes and came not near them all that might.</p>
               <p>What the Prieſt, and his diſtreſſed lover did after, that I could never learn, but the next morning, the old woman and I riſing early, we went down to ſee what was become of them, we found them both faſt aſleep, my Unkle in a Chair, and <hi>Matthew</hi> in the ſame poſture we had left him, we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:53678:59"/> the good man, who was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſtarv'd with cold, he at firſt wondred where he was, and told us that he had had a very ſtrange dream, which he would tell us at ſome other time, but now he was ſo cold and ſleepy that he would go to bed, he Chid us both for letting him fall a ſleep in a Chair in ſo cold a place, and ſo away he went: but firſt you muſt know that while he ſlept we had diveſted him of all his Church Ornaments, and had laid them out of the way, and ſet all things elſe in their right places, except <hi>Matthew,</hi> who was in a Corner of the Room, wedged in the frame of the Chair that he could not be got out.</p>
               <p>While I was getting the good man to bed, I told him, that when he ſhould wake again, I would give him an account of that dream he ſpoke of, at which having anſwer'd, that I was a fooliſh Girl, turn'd himſelf to ſleep. During the time I had employed my ſelf in laying the good Prieſt to bed: The Old woman had awakened <hi>Matthew,</hi> and with much ado got him out of
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:53678:60"/> the frame of the Chair, and having delivered him of the Chain that was about his neck, ſhe was comforting him, and endeavouring, as well as ſhe could, to perſwade him of the truth of the buſineſs, but he ſtill perſiſted in the belief, that all he had ſeen was real, while they two were thus ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing the caſe, ſome body knockt at the fore door, I went to ſee who it was, and I found it to be one of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thews</hi> Fathers Plowmen, that was come to inquire after <hi>Matthew,</hi> who he ſaid had not come home all night, I made him no other anſwer then that he ſhould go into the yard, and turn into the Room on his right hand, which he did; I durſt not appear, for fear of ſetting the fool into ſome new ſit, which would have made us been the longer troubled with him, and I car'd not how ſoon we were quit of him, <hi>Matthew</hi> was very glad to ſee <hi>Clunch</hi> ſo near him, who told him that his Father had ſent him to ſeek after him, who was much troubled at his abſence, and that he was very glad to have found him in ſo good a place,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:53678:60"/> I think you have all ploted to make me mad, ſaid <hi>Matthew,</hi> why, was not I at home, and in my own bed laſt night? No truly, reply'd <hi>Clunch,</hi> there was no body in all our houſe that did ſee you laſt night there, and no doubt but you would hardly a gone to bed without your Supper, beſides I ſhut all the doors at ten of the clock, and I am ſure that then you were not come home; well, reply'd <hi>Matthew,</hi> ſay what you will, and do what you will, but I know what I know, and feel what I feel, and think what I think, and I ſhall tell, my Father another ſtory when I get home, and ſo I'le be gone, then ſhak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his head, and leaning upon <hi>Clunch</hi> his ſhoulder, and dragging his legs after him, Good boy, continued he, I am going, but if ever you catch me h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re again, let all the Devils that tormented me laſt night, torment me ten thouſand times more, I that hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened to him all that while, got out of the way, that I might not be a new obſtacle to his going, ſo away went he, and his man <hi>Clunch</hi> together, and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:53678:61"/> from that time I never did ſee him more.</p>
               <p>When my Father was awake again the old woman and I were very buſie in perſwading him, that all which he had ſeen and done were real, but he would have it all a dream, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that do what we could, we could not perſwade him to the contrary, and that he began to be angry, thinking we play'd too long upon him; we left him in his own opinion, and ſo there was no more of that buſineſs talk'd of, at that time.</p>
               <p>How my Father and my poor Lover did make up the buſineſs between them, the next time they ſaw one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, I know not, but thus much I can tell you, that by this roguery of mine, I was for a long time freed from all manner of importunities on that Fools account.</p>
               <p>There reman'd ſtill my Bony <hi>Scot,</hi> to whom I ow'd a good turn alſo, which I promiſed within my ſelf to pay him ſo ſoon as I ſhould have an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to do it the good ſucceſs that I had ſo lately had with my other
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:53678:61"/> lover, did make me hope for as good a concluſion with this, but the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer being more fool than knave, and this more knave then fool, I was to manage my ſelf accordingly in my deſignes, which were eaſie to me, my natural inclination leading me alwayes to what was Roguiſh, and did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually furniſh me with ſtore of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, which made me not be long before I had given my <hi>Scot</hi> a diſh of my cooking, he having heard by ſome means or other, that my other Lover came not ſo frequntly to viſit me as he had done formerly, he took the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of his abſence, as all Rivalls do, to follow me cloſe and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſtrike me up before his Rival were aware of it, to that purpoſe he one day ſent me this Copy of verſes, they were ſo ridiculous and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, that with the often reading of them to make my ſelf and my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nions ſport, I got them by heart, thus they began.</p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:53678:62"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="poem">
                  <body>
                     <head>
                        <l>For the traſulently Beautiful <hi>Suſan.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>This Poetical rapture, I've ſet my Muſe on.</l>
                     </head>
                     <l>TRanſcendently, firmoſe, obſtreperous Beauty.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bartholomew</hi> your Servant, knows his duty.</l>
                     <l>He's too well known, to fail in the leaſt point,</l>
                     <l>And wholly yours he is through every joynt.</l>
                     <l>Therefore he makes bold to Salute in Rhin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Your ſelf gladly the Tree on which he'd climb.</l>
                     <l>The Font, in which he would water his Nag.</l>
                     <l>The Fort, on which he would diſplay his Flag.</l>
                     <l>Your ſelf, I ſay, who he would gladlier have</l>
                     <l>Then in Church-yard a fine new digg'd up Grave,</l>
                     <l>A broken ſhin, the Cramp, and the foul Squitter,</l>
                     <l>Or what's worth all, a piece of bread and Butter.</l>
                     <l>For, for in you, that is in your ſelf, ſweet,</l>
                     <l>Fairneſs and wiſdome in the Center meet;</l>
                     <l>You are Bellifick beyond <hi>Nell</hi> of <hi>Grecce</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Your Eyes are worth at leaſt Six pence a piece.</l>
                     <l>You have a Timbrel full of witty wit,</l>
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:53678:62"/>
                     <l>Y'are full of Grace, e'n when you cough or ſpit.</l>
                     <l>Your hands are leſs then a ſhoulder of Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</l>
                     <l>Your Feet and Legs are fit for Queen to ſtrut on.</l>
                     <l>And I'd rather ſee you, then my own heart,</l>
                     <l>Through which y'ave made ſuch a hole, that a Cart</l>
                     <l>Can ſcaree ſtop up the Gap, and I ſuppoſe,</l>
                     <l>If it ſinks long, you'l find it in my Hoſe.</l>
                     <l>For your ſweet ſake I'le drown'd, burn, rot, ſtink, hang.</l>
                     <l>Break leg, or arm, and my own dear ſides bang,</l>
                     <l>Therefore as you are fair, be gentle Lady,</l>
                     <l>To me your Serviture, as much as may be</l>
                     <l>And ſince to you I have given my heart</l>
                     <l>When next we meet lets never, never part</l>
                     <l>You are my hope, my joy, my Sugar Candy,</l>
                     <l>And I am your egregious Servant, <hi>Sawndy.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>How do you like them? Were they not high ſcrewd up, continued <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetta:</hi> I never heard any thing more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>idiculous and pleaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt in my Life, reply'd <hi>Le Noble,</hi> but thou haſt a moſt happy memory, I find, in waggery: we alwayes keep in our mind, you
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:53678:63"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:53678:63"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:53678:64"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:53678:64"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:53678:65"/> know reply'd <hi>Suſetta,</hi> thoſe things we like: thou art a baggage ſaid <hi>Le Noble,</hi> well prithy go on, for I long to hear how thou ordereſt this whyning Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, you ſhall not be long without it reply'd <hi>Suſetta,</hi> as you ſhall hear, I took this advantage to return him thanks for his good opinion, which he expreſs'd he had of me, as I perceiv'd by his paſſionate verſes, and bid the boy, that had brought them, to tell him, that I ſhould be glad to ſee him oftner, that I might have the happineſs to enjoy the more of his agreeable converſation, not doubting but a perſon ſo full of Poetical fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy's and wit as he was, muſt needs be extroardinary pleaſant company, and that I would have him make uſe of his Rivals abſence, in whoſe room I did long to ſee him. This was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough one would have thought to have made ſo hot a Lover, loſe not a moment of time: But he was of another opinion, and having found by the anſwer, which the boy return'd him, what a progreſs his Poetry had made in my heart, as he thought, he
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:53678:65"/> was reſolv'd to regale me in profe, before he would venture upon a viſit, thinking that one Letter more, would make me his aſſure as nothing more ſurer: In this opinion he writ this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which I receiv'd by the ſame Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger ſome two dayes after, with that ſhe pull'd it out of her pocket, and gave it to <hi>Le Noble</hi> who found it thus.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>To the ſuperlatively Supream Miſtreſs of my ſober affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Mrs. <hi>Suſetta.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>MAdam, Super-excellent, and the Imperial Miſtreſs of my wondrous Paſſions, pardon that my Perepatetick ſelf, does moſt profoundly entreat the Mixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick reſults of the Melliferous influences of you, Loxogonoſpherical intuition, you your own Individual ſelf, and none but your moſt ſublimated Lady, are able to produce, this Anthouſiaſme, in your more then thrice ſubmiſſimous admirer, give me leave ſuper Mundane Lady to become a moſt deſpicable ſupplicant at the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l of the pedeſtal of your more then
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:53678:66"/> thrice admirable ſtructure; and pardon him who ſubſcribes himſelf</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your ſlave, as far ſubterraneous to your pritty ſelf, as a Mirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donial inſect to the Altitude of the moſt Elevated Star,</hi> Sawndy <hi>alias</hi> Bartholomeus.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>There was never ſuch a medly of Nonſence ſeen before, ſaid <hi>Le Noble,</hi> having ended the Letter, I am glad I had it about me, ſaid <hi>Suſetta,</hi> I had taken it accidently with other Papers, when I made my eſcape from <hi>Roan</hi> or you had not now had that ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in reading it, nothing for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain can be more impertinent ſaid <hi>Le Noble:</hi> But, dear Girl, deprive me no longer from hearing how thou did it or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Coxcomb, I am drawing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it, reply'd <hi>Suſetta:</hi> But firſt you muſt know; that I, having read this Letter, was reſolv'd to bring him on, therefore I preſently writ him word, that I was ſo well ſatisfied with the knowledge of his great parts both in Poetry and in Proſe. That I
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:53678:66"/> ſhould think the time very long, till I did ſee him, which I fear'd would be more difficult than I had imagin'd, by reaſon that I had heard my Unkle exclaim very much againſt him that very day, but that in a very ſhort time I would give him notice how he ſhould come to me: that in the mean time, I deſired him, to let me hear frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from him, having ſealed and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected my Letter, I ſent it by this meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger.</p>
               <p>The next day about three a Clock in the morning, it being very dark my Scot comes under my Chamber Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and there having tun'd or rather untun'd an old broken Fiddle, he joyns his rank Voice to it, and Sang and ſcrap'd upon the Inſtrument thoſe verſes, which he had ſent me before to the Tune of
<q>
                     <l>Ariſe, Ariſe, open the Window</l>
                     <l>Ariſe, Ariſe, for it is day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But it would have made you ſick with laughing, had you but heard what pains he took and what ſtuff he made in the diſmembring of them, to fit them to that tune, and to inch them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:53678:67"/> with an A, at the end of a line B he was about the middle of his Song when ſo me body, out of a neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Window ſpoke to him, to leave off his Squeeking, becauſe he did di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the neighbour from ſleep with his ungrateful noiſe, but he was too buſie with his muſick, to mind any thing elſe, ſo that having been admoniſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> two or three times, to deſiſt, he at laſt was rewarded with a Potful of ſtuff, that did not ſmell altogether ſo ſweet as Musk, which did light ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckily upon his inſtrument, though thrown at a venture, that it daſh'd it all in peices, and beſpatter'd all his face, his hairs and his cloathes, as I heard him complain, I having got to the window ſo ſoon as I had heard him threatned, in hopes to have ſome ſport after he had made way to open his mouth, by wiping of his beard, (which he did alwayes were pretty long, out of Covetouſneſs, though he would have it paſs for gravity) he did revenge himſelf, by railing moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly againſt the actors of ſo ſoul a deed, with a world of threats of what he
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:53678:67"/> would do, did he but know from which window it came, having thus vented his Choler. To ſhew his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempory wit, he thus took leave of me.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Suſana ſweet your poor Servant beguiled</l>
                  <l>By foul diſtreſs, is all to be defiled,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ah Chamber pot not fill'd with ſweet Eſſence,</l>
                  <l>But what is worſe, with a Surreverence.</l>
                  <l>He Pardon begs for this his interruption,</l>
                  <l>And breaking off his Song, with ſuch ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uption</l>
                  <l>'Las it was not his fault he had proceeded,</l>
                  <l>Had his late Inſtrument been better heeded;</l>
                  <l>Sweet Miſtreſs <hi>Suſan,</hi> therefore pardon him,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe heart is full of love up to the brim</l>
                  <l>And leaſt you ſhould not know who was that ſaid it.</l>
                  <l>It was defil'd <hi>Sawndy,</hi> the ſame that made it.</l>
               </q>
               <p>This having been deliver'd in a moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oleful manner, and whyning tone, becauſe of the darkneſs which would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot have permitted me to ſee his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ne as) he ſcrapt a leg ſo hard up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lle ſtones, to make me hear, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Nailes he had in his ſhooes in a
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:53678:68"/> great number ſtruck fire, at which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was ſo pleas'd, that he repeated his r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence ſeveral times over, and ſo d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted. I having that night thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ht of a prank to play upon him the ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t morning, I ſent him a letter to gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> him many thanks for his fine M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, in which I did take much deligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, being at the Window liſtening after it, when that foul diſaſter had befall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> him, for which I was very ſorry, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that I did deſign to make him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends, that therefore I would have him come to our back door the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing night, between one and two, where I ſhould be ready to receive him.</p>
               <p>Having ſent this Letter ſeal'd up, I went to acquaint ſome of my Roguiſh Companions with my intentions, and invite them to take ſhare of the mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h in which they were to aſſiſt me, foul wanted help, they who deſired no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, did preſently give me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> aſſurance of their aid, the hour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed being come, we all lay in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſcade expecting his coming we were not long before we heard him coming. Now you muſt know that
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:53678:68"/> our houſe had a pretty long yard to it, at one end of which was the houſe we dwelt in, which went into a large ſtreet, and at the other end of the yard was a place where we kept fewel, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it a Chamber, which by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>allneſs of the Window and the Iron <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rs about it, did ſpeak it the reliques <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f, ſome ancient place of devotion which had fallen to decay. Nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>in'd ſtanding but what I have now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ntioned; he was no ſooner come near the door, but I and three of my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions diſguis'd like men ſeiz'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him and preſently muffling of him we hurried him away as to priſon, let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him underſtand by our diſcourſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> we went, that he muſt be the perſon which we had order to ſecure. The darkneſs of the night favouring us as much as could be, we had him round <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> one ſtreet into another, at laſt came back again upon our ſteps, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſently we drove him up ſtairs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, where having lockt the door upon him, there we left him in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rk: all the way he had been very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nportunate to know his Crime, and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:53678:69"/> very diligent in perſwading us that we took him for another, and that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> no other deſign that night, but to come to an aſſignation, which a Miſtreſs of his had given him. To which we made no other anſwer, but that the perſon we had order to ſeize on, was to come by that very place, where we had ſeiz'd him, and at that very moment: that we thought it was for High Treaſon, and concluded, that if he was innocent, no doubt but he would be releaſed, as ſoon as he ſhould make it appear, that till then he was to have patience, and this was all he could get out of us, when we had laid him ſafe, my Comrades retl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d each to their own houſe, and I went to bed.</p>
               <p>Now you muſt know that the room where we had pen'd up our Priſoner was commonly employ'd to keep Cheeſes in, my Unkle uſually letting it out for that purpoſe, out at that time it being in our own hands, there was nothing in it, but a little ſtraw ſcatter'd up and down; theſe did our amorous Scot ſpend that night
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:53678:69"/> no queſtion with leſs ſatisfaction and content, than he had promiſed to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf when he firſt ſet forth upon his amorous adventure. The next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we of the Siſterhood of Roguery, did meet, according to our appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and having debated what we ſhould do with our Priſoner, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd on this, which we preſently put in execution; we all got into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ower room, and there, as if we had then by chance in the ſtredt, we bid one another good morrow, under borrowed voices. Then wo began to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lk, of marketing and of our Maid ſervants, one ſaid to another, that ſhe had heard ſtrange news abroad, to which another ſaid, what concerning the great deſign that was lately diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd? I ſuppoſe, ſaid the third, that's all the Town talk, they ſay that there is a certain Scotchman in this priſon here that had an hand in it. Yes, rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>'d another in all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood, the world ſayes, his Proceſs is making ready, witneſſes have been heard, and it is reſolv'd that to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row morning, he is to be apply'd to
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:53678:70"/> the Rack, to make him confeſs his complices, well for my part, ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, I do not pity him in the leaſt, I would have all ſuch diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the publick quiet to be ſo ſerv'd? I wonder, ſaid another, that great perſons (as they muſt needs be that attempt ſuch great buſineſſes I ſhould admit of ſuch a pittiful ſcab by Raſcal amongſt them, as this ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry School-maſter is, who it is ſaid is not worth a groat, I'le aſſure you that I have heard it otherwiſe, reply'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, for ſome ſay, that he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, but that ſome perſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> knowing that he has a great deal of money they have accus'd him of being one of that plot, to make themſelves Maſters of all he has, and that it is to that purpoſe he is to be Rack<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that the torture and pain that he ſhall ſuffer, may make him ſay any thing to be quit of it, rather chooſing to give away his Life, then to endure the Rack in ordinary and extroardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, three times in four and twenty hours.</p>
               <p>Here my poor Lover, that had moſt
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:53678:70"/> diligently hearkened at our diſcourſe: not being able to hold any longer, broke out, into this doleful Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Yes, yes, there's the buſineſs: there's the knot of the buſineſs, that Gordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n knot: that nothing but the Sword of Juſtice can undo: It is money, my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oney, that renders poor <hi>Sawndy</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lty of all manner of Crimes, Oh! <hi>Sonpora,</hi> Oh! <hi>Mores,</hi> what an Age do we live in, that a poor man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in all his life time get ſomething to ſubſiſt with in his old Age, with all the care and penury, or induſtry imaginable. But he muſt preſently <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed by ſome Courtier, who hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he has got ſome money, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſently, through his power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, with the great ones, do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him to that extremity, I am in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Then with a great exclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. The Rack! The double Rack<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h Heavens! Continued he, well I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> already reſolv'd, they ſhall have all, all money and Life and all, rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en I'le endure ſuch Torture, the very thoughts of which does burſt my heart in ſunder, then fetching a
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:53678:71"/> great gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, we heard him fall upon the floor where he lay ſilent for a little while, after another grone he th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> continued, Oh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> my <hi>Suſetta,</hi> my dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt dear, <hi>Suſetta</hi> thou little thinks what's become of thy <hi>Sawndy,</hi> who is detained here in fowl diſtreſs, while you may think it is his own neglect Ah, that I could but let her, know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this my ſad adventure, if ſhe could not aſſiſt me, yet ſhe would pity me I am ſure, and that would be ſome content in my death, Oh that ſhe had all I am worth, that I might deceive thoſe that ſo thirſt after my blood f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the love of my Money? Oh my poor heart, Oh what thirſt do I enduge, Ah! now I feel the truth of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, which ſayes that ſorrow is dry; and if the drought is proportion, able to my ſorrow, what could not I drink now, Oh, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and having given two or three grones more, he lay ſilent. By this time I thought that my poor Lover had had a ſufficient Mortification, to allay in him all the pricks of the Fleſh, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id, me of him at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt for, ſome conſiderable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:53678:71"/> but being deſirous that he ſhould own his liberty to me alone, that I might the better intrap him again hereafter, if occaſion were, I reſolved to defer his deliverance till the next night a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that hour that we had brought him in, with that we retired to have ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fill with laughing, but didſt thou not afford him a little drink all that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaid <hi>Le Noble<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> not one drop, nor crum of bread, reply'd <hi>Suſetta</hi> Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, for Treaſon are not to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>'d ſo tenderly.</p>
               <p>Sir you cannot imagine what an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent thing is faſting during twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty four ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs, in order to a good ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>te, why? thou art them ſchieve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Rogue, that ever I heard of, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Le Noble,</hi> but prithy go on.</p>
               <p>The hour being come continued <hi>Suſetta,</hi> I came to my lovers priſon door with a dark Lantho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fter I had liſtened a while and heard him grone, ſigh and ſob; I call'd to him with a low voice, at which he ſaid do I not hear my ſelf call'd, then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently buſling up, I again call'd in the ſame low voice through the Key hole,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:53678:72"/> why <hi>Swandy</hi> my dear friend <hi>Swandy,</hi> will not anſwer thy dear <hi>Suſetta,</hi> at that he came as faſt as he could to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that place, where he thought the voice came, and there ſumbling with his hands about the door, was it a dream or do I awake, ſaid he, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ud, as being ſurpriz'd, with that I bid him ſpeak ſoftly if he would, not have us both, undone, and having aſſur'd him that I was there, I turn'd my Lanthorn, and opened the door and ſo came into him; telling him that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> might judge of my love by the many hazard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and dangers that I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſelf in for his ſake, for to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liver him from thoſe Torments which he was juſt going to endure a which would have no end but in death, and that I hop'd he would be ſenſible of this my kindneſs to him all his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> time, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th a thouſand Oaths and proteſtations, throwing himſelf a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty did aſſure me in his di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that all he was Maſter of, he would make mine, which he would make good as good as Law would make it ſo ſoon as he were at liberty, and paſt all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:53678:72"/> this did he confirm with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand kiſſes upon my hands and feet, having bid him put on an old Riding hood which I had brought with me on purpoſe that he might not be known as I pretended, with which I bid him cover all his face telling him that I would take care to conduct him, I grop'd my way down ſtairs, he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loving of me in the dark and having got into the ſtreet, he holding me by the Arm, I led him ſuch another jaunt as he had had the night before, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing round to our back door again, I bid him then ſhift for himſelf; that I durſt not adventure any further with him, but would now retire. I bid him remember when once he had got into a ſafe place, to ſend me word where he was, and how he did, after his impriſonment, which he having promiſed to do, and reiterated again all his vowes, and promiſes, he went his way, and I to bed, with a deſign to give an account to my comrades in the morning, of what I had acted that night, the day after I was think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what might become of my poor
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:53678:73"/> Lover, when there came an Old wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which brought me a ſmall Note well ſeal'd, in which I found this writ.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="poem">
                  <body>
                     <l>This is (as in all duty I am bound a)</l>
                     <l>To let you know that I am ſafe and ſound a,</l>
                     <l>Subſcribed 'tis from my old habitation</l>
                     <l>By him that can't forget his late Salvation</l>
                     <l>Heaven bleſs King Queen, the Family Royal</l>
                     <l>And make me ever to my <hi>Suſan</hi> Loyal.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>S.</hi> A. B.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>I inquired of the good woman how he did, who made me anſwer, that he was become very penſive ever ſince his late rambling, and that no body could get from him where he had been. During his twenty four hours abſence, neither would he be ſeen or ſpoken unto, that he had given her a ſpecial care to deliver that Note very privately into my own hands, with this the good woman ſighing, I am afraid continued ſhe, that he will fall ſuddainly very ſick, or at leaſt ſubſtracted with melancholly,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:53678:73"/> I making as if I pity'd him much, and having deſired the Old woman to remember me kindly to him, I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed her, with an aſſurance that I ſhould be alwayes glad to hear from him.</p>
               <p>After this I had no news of my Scotiſh Lovel till now of late by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the diſorders that I fell in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after, as follows,</p>
               <p>The Prieſt my good Unkle and my other Lover <hi>Matthew,</hi> by what means, I know not, were pieced up again, as great as ever: Nay, it had gone ſo far between the Father, the Son, and the Unkle, that a Marriage was concluded upon, though without the conſent of the Neece. One day my good Unkle being alone in his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, did ſend for me to him, and to make ſhort, after many admonitions and remonſtrances did poſitively con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that within a certain day, I ſhould prepare to be <hi>Matthew Clods</hi> Wife, I ſeeing that all the fair words and intreaties, that I made could not diſwade the Prieſt from this his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion, I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> laſt in a paſſion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt'd
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:53678:74"/> that I would run away, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy my ſelf, rather than to become the Wife to ſuch a Beaſt, and upon that in great rage I went out of the Old mans Chamber; my Unkle knowing that I was commonly as good as my word, in ſuch matters, reſolv'd to prevent me, in going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother way to work. Therefore having ſent his Old woman to call me back again, he told me that he had better conſidered of it, that he would not force me againſt my incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, that he would give me a longer time to reſolve my ſelf, and hoped I ſhould find in time the great good and advantage, which was intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me in that Match. This did ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing appeaſe me, and at leaſt made me not ſo haſtily put in execution, what I had deliberated within my ſelf. But, the old Fox prov'd that time too crafty for the young one, for towards Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the good Prieſt having call'd me to him, gave me a Letter, to carry to a certain Monaſtery of women, call'd <hi>La Filles Reparties,</hi> charging me to deliver it into the Abbeſſes own hands, I went
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:53678:74"/> to the Convent, inquired for the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Abeſſe, and gave her the Letter as I had been charged to do, ſo ſoon as ſhe had read it, looking upon me, ſhe bid me follow her, having brought me into a Parlour, ſhe call'd to her, two of the moſt grave women in the Company, here ſaid ſhe, to them, tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me by the hand: take this young Maiden into your ſafe cuſtody, and give me an account of her, when e're I call for it, I by this time ſeeing my ſelf trappan'd, I thought it was my beſt way to diſſemble, and with a chearful countenance, I told the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſs that I was very glad, my Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle had met ſo well with my own deſires, and that ſince it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for me to marry a perſon that I could never Love, I thought my ſelf the moſt happieſt Creature in the World, to be diſpoſed of in ſo good hands, and that I ſhould think the time long till I had gone through my year of probation, that I might take the vow; this pleas'd the Matrons and both my Guardians very well, who hoped they ſhould not be much troubled in look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:53678:75"/> after me, ſince that my own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations led me to it: that very night my trunk and all things elſe belonging to me, were ſent after me, with a Letter from my Uncle: In which there was Writ, that I had but two wayes to chooſe, either to reſolve upon marrying of <hi>Matthew Clod</hi> within ſix dayes, or to live all the reſidue of my Life in that place; I told the Meſſengers, that was wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for my anſwer, that ſince it was my Unkles pleaſure to have it ſo. Now that I had better thought of it, I was reſolv'd to obey him in all things, and that he ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, of me as he pleas'd.</p>
               <p>This unexpected anſwer, did ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce the Old mans heart when he, heard it, that the next day he ſent me a very kind Letter, with five new Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Leweſſes in it and a Diamond Ring, with which <hi>Matthew Clod</hi> had deſired, I ſhould preſented. This I thought did work very well in order to my future deſign, and ſeeming very well contented; It got me the liberty of the Cloyſter and the Garden. One
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:53678:75"/> day as I was walking towards Evening with ſome of the Nuns in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, perceiving a great Well with two large Buckets joyning to the Garden Wall, which was to furniſh Water for the Garden: my curioſity did lead me to look into it, ſo that I went thither alone, and as I caſt my eye in it, I ſaw a glimpſe of a Candle, and heard ſome perſons diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing. That made me the more c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rious, a while after I did perceive that the Candle was advanced into the Cavity of the well, through a Window towards the middle of it, and a little after, it was taken into the Window again, then I heard ſome body ſay. What a fine opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, would this be for ſome of the Nuns to ſteal out, or get a Gallant into them, if they did but know it: Eſpecially, now that this Common ſhore is dry, and while we are mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, I needed no more, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing took notice on which ſide the Window was, which was all over co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with a Company of Weeds, that grew round it, I preſently
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:53678:76"/> went to my Company again.</p>
               <p>Two Nights after, I took occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (after I had got about me all that I cared moſt for) to walk ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing later than ordinary in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and when I was ask't whether I would not yet retire, it growing dark, I made anſwer, that my head that had aked all that day, being much better, ſince I had been in the Air, I would enjoy the advantage of it ſo long as I could, ſo the reſt going in, I continued my walk, ſo ſoon as I ſaw the Coaſt clear, knowing that I ſhould not be long without being call'd for, I made towards the Well, where I haſtily ſet my ſelf in one of the Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, and holding with both my hands that part of the Rope, which was between the Pully and the other Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, I gently poys'd my ſelf down till I came to the Window, where having got in, I let go the Bucket again, which return'd to the ſame poſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, as before, I found my ſelf in a dark, low, ſlimy, wet place; which way to ſtir I knew not, nor which way to get out of it, that made me wiſh my
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:53678:76"/> ſelf in the Garden again, with all my heart. But conſidering, that it was not wiſhes but actions, that ſhould get me out again, now that I was in, I reſolv'd to go any way for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. It happen'd that I took that which after a long time brought me to the River ſide, where that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-ſhore did empty it ſelf, when it was running, I had ſo much light a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to perceive it was not even with the ground, but of what hight from it I could not judge; I ſet my ſelf down, to try whether my feet would then reach the ground, and as I was reaching out one foot as far as I could, the ſlimyneſs that was upon the ſtones, made me ſlip quite off and down came I to the ground, on which I fell ſo ſoft, that I had no other hurt than what the fear had giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me, ſo ſoon as I had recover'd my ſelf, I endeavoured to get from that naſty place, but I was ſo heavy with the great quantity of Mud that did ſtick very thick all about me, that I was forced to leave one of my pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticoats behind me, which I did ſink
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:53678:77"/> in the Mud, that it might not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray me, I had not gone far upon a Gravel and Sandy bank, but that I met with a Waterman in his Boat who ask'd me, how I came there, I told him, that in the dark I had accidentally fallen off of the bridge in a Muddy place, which had ſav'd me from hurting my ſelf, that if he would carry me over the Water, where I was going when I had fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, I would pay him well, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently took me into his Boat, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried me over: As we were croſing the Water, I ask't him, if he knew e're a houſe that I might go into to dry my ſelf, becauſe I was ſo wet, and dirty, that I could not go any further till I had made my ſelf clean, he told me that if I would go to his houſe, I ſhould be very welcome, and that I ſhould Lie in his Daughters bed with her, while his old Wife ſhould clean my Cloaths. I was glad to hear that, and did aſſure him to be grateful to him: We came on ſhore, and the good old man according to his word, did l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad me to his houſe, where a
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:53678:77"/> good fire was made, at which having very well warm'd and dry'd my ſelf I went to bed to the young Maiden, taking with me in my handkercheif, what I had in my pockets.</p>
               <p>In the morning early, my Cloaths were brought to me, very clean and dry, but much ſtain'd, with the blackneſs of the mud I was wiſhing that I had any other for them, they did ſo ſtink I told them; when the good woman looking over them very well, and finding that they were of fine ſtuff, and almoſt new, told me that if I pleas'd ſhe would give me her Daughters new petticote and Weſtcoat for them, and thank me to boot, I preſently agreed to it, and I had no ſooner put them on which fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me very well, but that the old woman told me, that by this change, ſhe was out of a great trouble which ſhe had been in, to get her Daughter ſome Wedding Cloaths, and that mine came very ſeaſonably; for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, I having given them ſomething for their pains, I deſired the good woman to let her Daughter guide me
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:53678:78"/> into the Road that went from <hi>Roan</hi> to <hi>Paris,</hi> and that then I ſhould find out my way home again well enough but that I did not know where I was at preſent the good woman did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently grant me my requeſt, and the young Maiden having brought me where I deſired, ſhe left me.</p>
               <p>I was very well pleas'd that I had ſo fortunately got into a dreſs that did ſo well diſguiſe me, I was walking along the Road when a Cart did overtake me, they that drove it ask'd me where I was going ſo early, I anſwered to the next Town, they told me, that if I would make them drink, they would carry me thither with that I having promis'd them a pot of Sider they got me up into the Cart where I reſted my ſelf, and was carried ſome three leagues towards <hi>Paris.</hi> I had not been long in the village after I had given thoſe fellows money to drink, but the ſtage Coach from <hi>Roan</hi> to <hi>Paris</hi> came by, there was but one paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger in it, and that was a woman, the Coach-man ſeeing me on foot told me that if I would go to <hi>Paris</hi> he
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:53678:78"/> would carry me thither very cheap, I told him that if he would carry me, but within half a days journey of <hi>Paris,</hi> I would give him content; we agreed upon two Crowns, of which the one I gave in hand, this was a great ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to me, eſpecially having the Company of a good Gentlewoman, who being pleas'd with my carriage and diſcourſe did take me for her bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>low, and paid for my diet all the way, at the dinner of the laſt day I p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id the Coach-man his other Crown, and ſo he went his way with the old Gentlewoman, and I ſtay'd behind, the place they had left me in, being a Market Town, and the next day Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t day, I had the curioſity to walk in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Market, and there amongſt the reſt of the Country Laſſes, I heard one ſhy to another that ſhe was weary of her place, becauſe it was an In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſhe not being us'd to be where Travellers and people of faſhion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted ſhe did not know how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have her ſelf amongſt perſons that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected ſo much attendance, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect which ſhe did not know how to
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:53678:79"/> pay them, that if ſhe could get any body to be in her ſtead me would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly reſign her place to them, and and return home to her Father to look after the dary which was her element, this diſcourſe made me think that it might prove a good place for me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire unto, (I daring, not truſt my ſelf to that little world <hi>Paris</hi>) and there ſtay; till I heard news from my friends, and how my concerns did ſtand at <hi>Roan,</hi> I addreſſed my ſelf to the Maid, and told her that if ſhe would help me to that place, ſhe had newly mention'd, I ſhould be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to her. The Maid preſently made me anſwer that if I would go with her ſhe would carry me thither behind her, not doubting but that my good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>em would give me a welcome.</p>
               <p>The thing prov'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s the Maid had ſaid; for ſhe had no ſooner ſhew'd me to her Maſter, and told him that ſhe had provided me to be in her place, but he ſeem'd to be very well pleas'd at it, and ſo I was entertained. That night I lay with that Maid who I was to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed; ſhe inform'd, me of the work
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:53678:79"/> which I was to do, which was about the Chambers. The next morning I gave her thanks, with ſomething to buy her a pair of Gloves, after which ſhe went her wayes, and I remain'd in her Room.</p>
               <p>It was in that place, where about a fortnight after, I had the good fortune to be inſtrumental in the preſervation of my dear <hi>Le Noble,</hi> for which I ſhall ever be thankful to my Stars, for hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by that means, endear'd my ſelf to you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Le Noble</hi> having kiſs'd and given her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thouſand, thanks for her pleaſant ſtory, and thoſe kind expreſſions that ſhe concluded it withal. But my Dear <hi>Suſetta,</hi> continu'd he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> In all thy Travels, hadſt thou never any affronts offer'd thee? Nor no attempts upon thy cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity? My dear <hi>Le Noble,</hi> reply'd <hi>Suſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta:</hi> It is not ſo long, ſince I have giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en my ſelf up unto thee without any reſerve, that I ſhould ſo ſoon forget it. I cannot deny, but that diuers at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts have been made upon me, by ſuch as had a good opinion of my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, though not ſo of my Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:53678:80"/> But beſides the aſſurance that I now give thee, that never any body did ſucceed; thou ſhalt find, that I come a pure Maid into thy embraces. With that hiding her bluſhes in his boſome. Think not the worſe of me, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhe, my dear <hi>Le Noble,</hi> for being ſo free with thee, but attribute this to my Natural humour, and remember that I will be as true and faithful to thee, as if we were married according to all thoſe formalities, which the Law of the Land does require, I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that I am young and wild; yet I am not ſo ignorant, but that I know Marriage to be the Union of man and woman together, by the ties of ſincere Vows and Proteſtations, to be faithful and true to one another, and ſo to live together in conſtant Love and mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al affection, till thoſe Vowes be diſſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the death of one of the parties, or by the mutual conſent of both? But what the Laws and Cuſtomes bind us unto, are things brought in to neceſſary conveniences, and not entirely eſſential. Nay, I know f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rther, contined ſhe, that men will and
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:53678:80"/> do commonly take more liberty in the State of Marriage; then the modeſty of our Sex does uſually allow us. Therefore I ſhall not wonder, if my dear <hi>Le Noble,</hi> does as the reſt of men: But one thing I ſhall deſire, that he would promiſe me: which is, that he would ever prefer me in his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to all others, and as to the reſt, let him take his liberty, which I freely do grant to him.</p>
               <p>Theſe kind expreſſions from <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetta,</hi> could not but make a great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon <hi>Le Nobles</hi> generous ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, who in gratitude, did return her many kind aſſurances that he would ever have an high eſteem for her, and more love than for any one elſe. That he would never conſent to a ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on except they both did ſee an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable neceſſity for it, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe would render them both mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable; that he had too tender an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for her, to purchaſe his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and ſatisfaction, at ſo dear a rate as her ruine. With that having a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, given one another a thouſand kiſſes, and as many other teſtimonies
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:53678:81"/> and aſſurances of affections, they went to Supper, <hi>Suſetta</hi> promiſing <hi>Le Noble,</hi> to give him after Supper a full account of what had happened to her, during his ſtay at <hi>Paris,</hi> which ſhe told him, would be worth his hearing.</p>
               <p>They having Supp'd, and the Cloath taken away, <hi>Suſetta</hi> continued her Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as followes,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Continuation of <hi>Suſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi>'s Story.</head>
               <p>I Do ſuppoſe, that you might be got to <hi>Paris,</hi> when the Hoſt my Maſter return'd home without the Curate, who I did never ſee after, but my Maſter I perceiv'd came back ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſcontented, and ſo out of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour that he did vent his choler upon every one in the houſe but me, which made me hope that they had miſt of you, and that you were got ſafe to <hi>Paris,</hi> a while after he retired himſelf to his Chamber, and gave ſpecial or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53678:81"/> to all his Servants, not to ſay, that he was in the houſe, but if any body ſhould come to ask after him, they ſhould tell them, that he was gone to ſee a Brother of his, that was dying, and whoſe Heir he expected to be after that, my Maſter would all day long keep within his Chamber locked up; and at Nights he would take his Horſe, ride out, and come home again in the Morning before day: This had continued five or ſix weeks, when one Night there came in a Gentleman on Horſeback, to Sup and Lye at our houſe, he preſently call'd to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted to a bed Chamber, which was accordingly done: I perceived that he had lookt very earneſtly upon me, by the way to his Chamber, he gave charge that a Supper ſhould be got ready with all diligence, for he would make haſte to bed, that he might be gone in the morning before day. An hour after I was call'd for up, to that Gentleman; I came, and I found my Maſter very merry with him, and buſie in diſcourſe, which made me offer to go back again, thinking that
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:53678:82"/> my Maſter had ſupply'd him, with what he wanted, but my Maſter ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to the door, and taking me by the hand, did pull me by force, and and then ſhov'd me into the Travellers arms, ſaying, take her, ſhe is yours: to which I anſwer'd, that there were more than two words to that bargain, and that though I was his Servant for the preſent, yet ſo long as I was not his Slave, he had no right to Give or Sell me; my Maſter told the Gentleman, that he ſhould not mind my talk, that I was a young fooliſh Girl, but that he ſhould teach me better things in a ſhort time, with that the ſtranger beginning to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing rude, I proteſted that if he would not deſiſt, I would ſhrick or call out ſo loud, that the whole houſe, and all the Neighbourhood ſhould hear me, with that the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman did let me go, and I preſently flung out of the Chamber, and would not come there any more, but I went immediately to a good old wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans houſe our next Neighbour, whence notwithſtanding all they
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:53678:82"/> could do or ſay, I did not return home, till news were brought me that the Gentleman and my Maſter were gone to bed. When I found the Coaſt clear, I went and lay upon my bed with my Cloaths on, where I had not been two hours, but that my Chamber door was broke open, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſeiz'd on, gagg'd, and bound, and ſet before a man on Horſeback, who carried me away in the dark and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the Night, notwithſtanding all the reſiſtance that I could make, we had not rid two Leagues, when we were overtaken by the Gentleman, who had offered ſome rudeneſs to me the night before: It was then juſt break of day, which afforded as much light, as ſerved me for to know him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, at the ſight of him, I conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that their deſign was to raviſh me, and after that to cut my Throat and caſt me into ſome hole: Theſe appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions ſeizing on my Spirits all at once, and on ſuch a ſudden made me fall into a ſwound, which being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd by him, that held me on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, they got me off of the Horſe,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:53678:83"/> in a place out of the Rode, where when I came to my ſelf again, I found that I was unbound, ungagg'd, and unlaced, the Gentleman holding my head in his lap, while his man was gone to look for water, with which he return'd a little after I had come to my ſelf again. I began to ſtruggle a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and offer to get my head from his lap, when he thus ſpoke to me with a diſcompos'd voice and a trembling fit, which I was ſenſible was upon him.</p>
               <p>Fair Maid, if it is your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to have your head off of me, at leaſt be pleas'd to reſt it againſt this Tree, while you hear what I ſhall ſay, with that having laid his Cloak in a heap againſt the Tree, he laid my head upon it, end afterwards did thus conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue his diſcourſe: Had not that baſe man your Maſter given me an ill cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of you, I had never made any further attempt upon your Chaſtity; for I was ſo fully perſwaded by your firſt reſiſtance, and the high reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which you expreſſed laſt night, both in your words and actions, that
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:53678:83"/> I had never attempted any thing fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but that he did aſſure me, that it was not the firſt time you had done ſo with others, to whom you had freely yeilded to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> laſt, theſe words, and his aſſurance, that he would bring you to yield to go away with me in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, made me pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t with twenty Piſtols, which I had bargained with him for you. But now, that I find you quite another perſon, then he repreſented you to me; I hear do ſwear, by all that is ſacred to offer you, not the leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, and I do moſt heartily beg your pardon, for what I have done, aſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing you, that if ever I can gain your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections with kindneſſes and ſervices, I ſhall think my ſelf moſt happy, out that I will never endeavour to make my ſelf ſo by any baſe means, for proof whereof, continued he, if you pleaſe <hi>I</hi> ſhall immediately return you back, or carry you to any other place, you ſhall pleaſe to command me, he further added, that if her Maſter had not aſſur'd him, that <hi>I</hi> was gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore very well ſatisfied, he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have come after me, but to have
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:53678:84"/> brought me back again, as he was ſtill ready to do.</p>
               <p>Theſe things with ſome more he did ſpeak with ſuch an ayr and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, as made me give credit to what he ſaid, which having ſomewhat re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv'd my Spirits, <hi>I</hi> thus reply'd to him, Sir, to ſhew you that <hi>I</hi> give faith to your words, <hi>I</hi> humbly beg of you on my knees, that you would take pity on a poor diſtreſſed young Maid, and according to theſe aſſurances, you have given me of your civil carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me for the future, you would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pleas'd to carry me any whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, but where that Monſter is. If it were your conveniency, <hi>I</hi> continu'd, <hi>I</hi> had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ther go to <hi>Cane,</hi> than any where elſe: But, <hi>I</hi> fear, it is too far, at which the Gentleman, did preſently reply, that though he could not get thither, without the hazard of his Life, yet to ſhew me, that nothing ſhould deter him from ſerving me with all his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, he would conduct me there, being confident, by my diſcourſe and actions, that <hi>I</hi> was another perſon that <hi>I</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for, and ſuch a one as he did not
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:53678:84"/> doubt but did deſerve a thouſand times more and greater ſervices, I having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd him, that if I once got ſafe to <hi>Cane,</hi> by his meanes, he might know ſomething further of my condition, he ſet me one horſe back, behind that fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that had carried me out of the Inn, where I did ſit, till we came to the next place, where I might be fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſuch things as were neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for a woman that rides on horſe back.</p>
               <p>About two hours after we came to a Market Town, where I was put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Coach, which by good fortune was going to <hi>Cane,</hi> in which there was an empty place; It was a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Coach, but my Gentleman did prevail with the Company in it, to let me have a place, and giving ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the Coachman he had the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, to tye a Cloak bag behind the Coach, which did much eaſe his mans horſe, that otherwiſe muſt have been left behind; having eaten ſomething for breakfaſt, and treated the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany that was in the Coach, which were but Servants that tended upon
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:53678:85"/> two young Children: the Coachman drove towards <hi>Cane,</hi> at dinner time my Gentleman did again treat the whole Company for my ſake, and ſhewed me much more reſpect than my habit did require, which made the Company do the like, though they wondred at it, eſpecially at his great care of me, never abandoning the Coach-ſide on horſe back, ſo long as I was in it;</p>
               <p>It was about the dusk of the even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and we had not above three or four miles farther to go to our Inn that night, when there ſuddenly came half adozen men well mounted, upon a full ſpeed, they preſently ſeiz'd on the Coach-horſes, and having cut their harneſſes turn'd them looſe, while o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were buſie about my Gentleman, who making reſiſtance, was ſhot with a brace of Bullets through the head, with which he fell off of his horſe ſtone dead, the Coach was preſently ranſackt, the Gentlemans man ſo ſoon as he ſaw his Maſter on the ground, fled as faſt as his horſe could carry him, and all the goods that were in the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:53678:85"/> Coach, were taken out and carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; this buſineſs was done on ſuch a ſudden and with ſuch diſpatch, that there was not much more time ſpent in the execution, then I have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in the relation of it; ſince my getting out of the Convent I had alwayes carried all the gold I had with the Diamond Ring in a little purſe, which I conſtantly wore in my boſome, day and night, in that alſo was the Ring which you had given me, thoſe that robb'd us had not had time to ſtrip us, by that means I ſav'd all <hi>I</hi> had, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſome Silver, which was in my poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, my papers <hi>I</hi> found again ſcatter'd about the Coach, and upon the Road, and the ſmall bundle of Cloaths, which did belong to me that had been given to the fellow, that carried me away, <hi>I</hi> found afterwards by good fortune in in that Cloak bag, which belong'd to the dead Gentleman, it had been taken up on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oad by ſome Servants that belong'd to a company of Gentlemen, which came up to us, not above a quarter of an hour after, we had been robb'd, who finding us in that ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:53678:86"/> did preſently conclude, that thoſe perſons they had met were they, that had done the deed, who knowing by their ſpies, that they were too ſtrong a party, and ſo near them, it had made them make ſuch extraordinary haſt in plundering us, one of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen asking whoſe Cloak bag that was, one of the Coach company made anſwer that it was mine, upon that it was given me, the firſt thing that was done after they had found no life left in the poor Murdered Gentleman, was to ſend their Servants, which were ſix in number, ſome to get the Coach hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and the Gentlemans alſo, which was run away after the Coach horſes, ſo ſoon as his Maſter was fallen, and and the reſt to Gallop to the next town, to get ſome conveniency to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the dead body thither, mean time the Gentlemen began to examine to whom the Coach did belong, and thoſe pritty Children, that were in it the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants did anſwer, that they belonged to a Gentleman, which they named, which they had been to fetch from their Grandmothers, where they had been for
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:53678:86"/> ſome time, and that they were going with them to their Fathes houſe, who liv'd within two or three leagues of <hi>Cane,</hi> this made the Gentlemen the more ready and diligent in aſſiſting us, becauſe they knew the Gentleman, and there was ſuch care taken, that in two hours time there came a Cart in which the dead body was lay'd, and the Harneſs of the Coach were made fit to carry us to the Inn, where we were conducted by the Gentlemen: during the way, <hi>I</hi> having told my company that <hi>I</hi> was a meer ſtranger to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, <hi>I</hi> earneſtly entreated two wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that were in the Coach, to own me as one of their fellow ſervants, as they might perceive, that the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men did take me to be, which they promis'd me to do, and they were as good as their word, and very civil to me all the way, concluding that it was my good face that had made the Gentleman ſo kind to me, of which kindneſſes they had been made large partakers; being come into the Inn, we women and the Children where pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently had into one room, where
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:53678:87"/> there was three beds, as we had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired. There we ſupp'd altogether, lockt our ſelves in, and had a great deal of Womens that, amongſt which <hi>I</hi> gave them a particular account of what had ſo lately befallen to me.</p>
               <p>I being out of danger as I thought, and my fears being blown over, I had got into a jolly humour, which did pleaſe my company ſo well, that they declar'd they were very glad they had met with ſo good company as I was, then in a merry humour having ſhew'd them, by pulling my Purſe out of my Boſome, how I had fruſtrated the Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of a good Booty, they having loſt all their money. After they had look'd a pritty while upon the two Rings they ſaid, that they did imagine that I was ſome other perſon than I appear'd to he, which now I had confirm'd, I being deſirous to draw them ſtill more and more into a good opinion of me, that <hi>I</hi> might keep my place the reſt of the jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in the Coach, without which I did not know what I ſhould do. I told them <hi>I</hi> was a Gentlemans Daughter of <hi>Roan.</hi>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:53678:87"/> Who having been compell'd, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe my Parents that I would marry a perſon that I could not Love, to ſhun a Recluſe Life in a Monaſtry, I had the day before the Marrige, ſtoln away from them; That my deſign in going now to <hi>Cane,</hi> where I had ſome Relation, was to learn in ſome diſguiſe, how my affairs ſtood there, and endeavour my Peace with my Parents, with whom I ſhould never be reconcil'd without the breaking off of that match, which <hi>I</hi> did ſo abhor, that I would rather chuſe death than it. That thereform, I earneſtly begg'd of them to aſſiſt mo in what they could, they not knowing how ſoon it might be their condition: To this I added, that <hi>I</hi> had a great mind to dreſs me in mans apparel, both to keep me from being known, as alſo becauſe <hi>I</hi> thought it the ſafeſt qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſecure me for the future, from ſuch dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers as <hi>I</hi> had ſo lately eſcaped. <hi>I</hi> ſpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> theſe things with ſo much paſſion and tenderneſs, that <hi>I</hi> won them wholly to me, one of them promiſing, that ſhe would bring me to her Mothers houſe, that was not far from that place where
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:53678:88"/> they were going, and within two little leagues of <hi>Cane,</hi> where <hi>I</hi> ſhould be very welcome, and where <hi>I</hi> ſhould receive all manner of civil uſage and ſervices, ſuch as good Countrey people could afford.</p>
               <p>From that time, I was treated with more reſpect than before, and when we were weary of chatting it grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing late, they gave me the choice of a bed by my ſelf, where I ſlept all night without awaking: To make ſhort, my dear heart, we all got ſafe to our jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies end, I was conducted to the maid's Mothers houſe, where while a mans black ſuit, which was with other things in the Cloak bag, fitting for me, I ſent to <hi>Cane</hi> for a Perriwig, a Hat, a Sword, and all other things fitting to make me a compleat Cavaller, having all things ready to appear in publick, after I had return'd the people of the Houſe many thanks for all their kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to me, I went to <hi>Cane,</hi> where I was no ſooner arriv'd, but I got a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, who carried me a Letter to my Scotch Lover, from whom I thought, I ſhould get a better account
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:53678:88"/> then any body elſe could give me of all my concerns: Not doubting, but that his Love to me, would have made him very inqulſitive after me, and that the ſame love would quickly bring him to me. If I did but in the leaſt deſire it: Not doubting, but to ſhake him off a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, when I ſhould think it convenient. The Letter was much to this purpoſe.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>
                           <hi>My dear</hi> Sawndy,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>WHen I have aſſur'd you, that all which I have lately acted, was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in order to preſerve my ſelf for you, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, I ſhall not need to make uſe of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inducements to bring you to me, then to let you know where I am. Therefore I invite you to make all the haſte you can poſſible to come to the white horſe in <hi>Cane,</hi> where you will find ſhe that is only yours,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Suſetta.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Meſſenger that carried it, found him deſperately ill, in ſo much that he thought, he could not live to the Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies end, that he had been ſo overjoy'd at the reception of my Letter, that he had immediately given order to get a
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:53678:89"/> Litter ready to carry him the next morning out of Town, to take the air, as he pretended, with that he gave me a Letter from him, and <hi>I</hi> aſſure you, Sir, continu'd the fellow: No Lover, could have made more Careſſes to a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, from his beloved Miſtreſs, than he made of yours, which he believ'd he had ſeen him kiſs twenty times, and read as often over in private; and that every body in the houſe were wondring at ſo great a change in him, which made them very inquiſitive to know of me, whether it came not from a young Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman. I told my Meſſenger, to take of all ſuſpition, that though it came from me, yet, that there was ſuch news in it from a Gentlewoman; as would as much pleaſe him But ſince he is ſo ill as you ſay, <hi>I</hi> have a mind to meet him upon the Rode, leaſt his death ſhould prevent me from accompliſhing that good office which <hi>I</hi> have promiſed my kinſwoman to do for her having thus ſaid to the Meſſenger, <hi>I</hi> opened the Letter, in which, <hi>I</hi> read as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows</p>
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:53678:89"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <l>MY deareſt, deareſt Dear, thy half dead <hi>Sawndy.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>By ſtrength of Love with Litter and burnt Brandy.</l>
                     <l>Will run through, Fire, Air, Earth, and Water too.</l>
                     <l>Through thick and thin, over Boot, over Shoo.</l>
                     <l>To come to thee: with ſickneſs I'm ſo preſt.</l>
                     <l>I can no more, let Porter tell the reſt.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>S.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>By this <hi>I</hi> found though he could not leave off his Plague of Rhime, that he was really very ill, of which <hi>I</hi> did inform the Meſſenger; who told me that he had ſwounded twice away the Writing of thoſe few lines, about which he had ſpent two hours time at leaſt. This made me employ this fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, to get me immediately a Horſe, to be going that very day to meet him.</p>
               <p>Mean time <hi>I</hi> was very well pleas'd within my ſelf at all this, by which <hi>I</hi> found <hi>I</hi> ſhould the ſooner and the eaſier compaſs my ends, then <hi>I</hi> could
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:53678:90"/> ever have imagin'd, if <hi>I</hi> did but find him alive. The fellow having got me a Horſe: We both preſently ſet forwards, we were got a little above halfway to <hi>Roan,</hi> where we met with my poor <hi>Lover,</hi> who was laid in bed in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Inn of a Market Town: Not being able to purſue his Journey any further. He had been ſo prudent, not to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a word of me to any body; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when <hi>I</hi> came to his bedſide, tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him by the hand, <hi>I</hi> did ſoftly whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in his ear, that <hi>I</hi> was his <hi>Suſetta,</hi> come to meet him in that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe, that <hi>I</hi> might not be diſcover'd: He preſently ſtarted up, holding me faſt by the hand with both his, and having given order that every body in the room, ſhould retire: He did endeavour to expreſs, as well as he could, what joy he receiv'd at the ſight of me. Though he fear'd that it was too late to continue long, the grief which he had taken for my loſs, having come ſo near his heart, that it had reduc'd him to that ſad extremity, in which <hi>I</hi> ſaw him. Adding that his greateſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:53678:90"/> had been how to order things ſo, that in caſe <hi>I</hi> ſhould ever be found again, <hi>I</hi> ſhould inherit all that he would leave to me at his deceaſe: That <hi>I</hi> ſhould now paſs for a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew of his, though he had no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation that he knew of, and that he would forthwith make his Will, but if it were poſſible, he would willingly be remov'd to ſome private houſe out of Town, becauſe that the perpetual noiſe of that place he was in would not let him take any reſt. And ſo he concluded, <hi>I</hi> having return'd him many thanks, and once more aſſur'd him of my affections, we broke off our private diſcourſe: He having bid me call for <hi>Megerlain,</hi> to whom he gave order to get things ready to remove peſently: He deſired that <hi>I</hi> ſhould retire to take my Reſt, while he would endeavour to do the like, to make him the more able to endure the Removing; with that he turn'd to ſleep, and <hi>I</hi> went to another Room, where having call'd for a Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Ink to Write for an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Phyſician at <hi>Paris,</hi> to come
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:53678:91"/> to my Unkle (as <hi>I</hi> call'd him) <hi>I</hi> Writ that Letter, which brought you to me. Not long after, I was call'd to him again, he not being able to reſt for the Noiſe, he bid me take care of his Removal, which I preſently order'd: We were no ſooner come to the Houſe, which I had caus'd to be taken for him, but he call'd for all the pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to it, and, in the preſence of them all, he did declare, that <hi>I</hi> was his Nephew, and next Heir at Law, and that he would have every body, follow my directions.</p>
               <p>This was the place wherein I had f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> the happineſs to embrace my Dear <hi>Le Noble,</hi> who, I hope, will not have the worſe opinion of his poor <hi>Suſetta,</hi> for having given him ſo true and juſt an account of her whole Life, ſince it was in obedience to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Le Noble</hi> having thank'd her and aſſured her, that if it were poſſible to Love her more then he did already, the Candidneſs ſhe had us'd in the delivery of her own ſtory, and the
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:53678:91"/> freeneſs which he found in all her other diſcourſes and actions, would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it. That he intreated her to believe, that he really and cordially did love her, and would e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver continue ſo to do, with that <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetta</hi> ſeeming deſirous to ſleep, <hi>Le No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> having taken his leave of her, was retiring into his Chamber, which was on the other ſide of the houſe, when <hi>Suſetta,</hi> calling him back, told him, that hence forwards ſhe would diſcharge her ſelf on him, of the troubleſome office of Purſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer, ſo deſired that he ſhould take that which lay upon the Table along with him, and the Writings of concern: <hi>Le Noble</hi> reply'd, I will obey you in all things; and thruſting his hand into the Purſe, he took out a handful of Gold and Silver mix'd together, and which laying upon the Table, but leaſt you ſhould be too troubleſome, continued he, with frequent demanding for Pins and ſuch like trifles, let this lye by you, to ſupply you with ſuch dayly occaſions, and preſently draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:53678:92"/> the door cloſe after him, to take from her all occaſion of reply, he retired to his Chamber, where I will leave him till the next Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which will produce ſome New Adventure, wherewith to begin the Second Part.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the Firſt Part.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:53678:92"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>William Cade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> at the Popes head in the New <hi>Exchange.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>Folio.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>PHaramond</hi> Compleat, in Engliſh</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clelia</hi> a Romance compleat, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Parthaniſſa</hi> in ſix parts.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Heylins</hi> Coſmography.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>William Howells</hi> Hiſtory of the World in two vollums, now in the preſs.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Quarto.</head>
               <item>The Proteſtant Religion is a ſure foundation, by the right Honorable the Earl of <hi>Derby.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Jeſuits</hi> policy to ſuppreſs Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy by a perſon of Honour.</item>
               <item>Fair warning in two Viſitation Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, by Dr. <hi>Seth Buſhell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The great efficacy of the Clergy, a Viſitation Sermon, by Dr. <hi>Duncomb.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of the Iſland of <hi>Madera.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Sermon preached before the King by Mr. <hi>Barne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Sermon preached at the Aſſizes at <hi>Lancaſter</hi> by Mr. <hi>Bigol.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:53678:93"/>
            <list>
               <head>Octavo and Twelves.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Hiſtory.</item>
               <item>Reflections upon Antient and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Phyloſophy.</item>
               <item>Engliſh Princeſs, or the Dutcheſs Queen, a pleaſant Novel.</item>
               <item>Court Songs being an exact Collection.</item>
               <item>The Temple of Death with other Poems by a perſon of Honour.</item>
               <item>The Dutch <hi>Hudebraſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Liquor <hi>Alchaheſt,</hi> or the immortal diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvent of <hi>Paracelſus</hi> and <hi>Helmont, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Phyloſophical <hi>Eſſay,</hi> or the Hiſtory of Petrification, by Dr. <hi>Sherley.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hiſtory of Scurvey graſs, by Dr. <hi>Sherly</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Treatiſe of the Gout, by Dr. <hi>Sherly.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Guilm. Ferraris de bello Battavico.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Quibles being very pleaſant</item>
               <item>The Amours of Count <hi>Dunois,</hi> a witty Novel.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Zayde</hi> a Spaniſh Novel, in two parts</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mazarines</hi> Memoirs a Novil</item>
               <item>Penitent Hormit both pleaſant Novels.</item>
               <item>Engliſh Monſieur both pleaſant Novels.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clarks Manuel</hi> a book of Preſidents.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Saunders</hi> his Aſtrological Phyſicks.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Anima Mundi</hi> by <hi>Ch. Blount, Gent.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:53678:93"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
